<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A name, an after-one, or, Onoma Kainon, a name, a new one in the later-day-glory, or, An historical declaration of the life of Shem Acher especially as to some more eminent passages of his day relating to his more thorow lawful call to the office and work of the ministry for about twenty years last past. ...</title>
            <author>Bampfield, Francis, 1615 or 16-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12256069</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12256069</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 163:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A name, an after-one, or, Onoma Kainon, a name, a new one in the later-day-glory, or, An historical declaration of the life of Shem Acher especially as to some more eminent passages of his day relating to his more thorow lawful call to the office and work of the ministry for about twenty years last past. ...</title>
                  <author>Bampfield, Francis, 1615 or 16-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Hebrew at head of title.</note>
                  <note>Parts of title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>"Shem Acher" is Francis Bampfield's pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. 38.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57500:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> A NAME, an After-one; OR, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A NAME, a New One, <hi>In the Later-Day-Glory:</hi> OR, AN Hiſtorical Declaration OF THE <hi>Life of Shem Acher,</hi> Eſpecially as to ſome more eminent Paſſages of his Day, relating to his more thorow lawful Call to the Office and Work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, for about Twenty Years laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>Wherein <hi>PAUL</hi> is propounded for an Example, and the Caſe, ſo far as it doth run Parallel, is ſet down before it; tho the Preheminence is given unto <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Glory of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in every part, and in the whole of it, unto <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> whoſe rich Grace, and free Love has been, in all this, unſearchably rich and exceedingly abundant.</p>
            <p>Wherein are alſo ſeveral other weighty Caſes, and great Queſtions ſtated and reſolved, About the Right Adminiſtrator in perfecting a Believer's Baptiſm; About Receiving of a Member in ſome Caſes out of one Church in the ſame City into another Church of the ſame City, in the Main of the ſame Goſpel-Faith and Order: And about the ſound Evidences of a State of Grace.</p>
            <p>All ſubmitted to Scripture-Counſel, Number, Meaſure and Weight; to Word-Rule-Trial-Judgment-and Determination. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 11, 15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the Angel near the Royal Exchange in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57500:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57500:2"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Hiſtorical Declaration</hi> OF THE LIFE OF <hi>Shem Acher.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L</hi> had <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 13. 9. Gal. 1. 1. Acts 9. 1, 4, 8, 11, 17, 19, 22, 24, 26. and in many other places.</note> another Name, which was <hi>Saul:</hi> This other Name was an Hebrew Name, ſignifying, <hi>Asked, Deſired,</hi> or <hi>Petitioned.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shem Acher</hi> is an Hebrew Name, ſignifying an <hi>After-Name,</hi> or a Name an <hi>After one;</hi> to which he was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the LORD, in a ſuitable <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 65. 15.</note> Scripture, upon that new State, which he through Grace paſſed into.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3. 4, 5, 6. Act. 21. 39. &amp; 22. 3. Rom. 11. 1. 2 Cor. 2. 22. Act. 24. 14. &amp; 26. 6, 7. &amp; 28. 17, 19, 20. Rom. 9. 3. &amp; 11. 14. Act. 22. 3. Gal. 1. 14. Acts 23. 6. &amp; 26. 5. &amp; 7. 58. &amp; 8. 1. &amp; 9. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 13, 14, 21, 26. &amp; 22. 4, 5, 19, 20. &amp; 26. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. 1 Cor. 15. 9. Gal. 1. 13, 23. 1 Tim. 1. 13. Mat. 23. 13,—33.</note> If outward Priviledges had had any thing in them to have bin boaſted of, he had enough to ſay concerning that; For, he was by birth an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> or <hi>Jew, an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew of the Hebrews,</hi> both his Parents being ſuch: which race of People had many Favours and Dignities conferred upon them by the LORD, beyond other Nations; He was of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> which was a Tribe ſignally honoured in many reſpects: He was educated in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a Diſciple and a Pupil under the teaching and tutorage of that Doctor of the Law, thus bred up in their School and College: He was inſtituted and inſtructed in <hi>Phariſaiſm,</hi> of which Sect and Way his Father and other Anceſtors were; and thus was he trained up from his Youth, being very zealous for their Common-Prayer-Book and Church-Canons, and other human Traditions. And thus he continued till about the three or four or five and twentieth year of his Age, when in a falſe and blind Zeal he cruelly perſecuted Chriſt, and the Church and Diſciples of Chriſt, breathing out Threatnings and Slaughter againſt them; thinking verily with himſelf, that he ought to do many things contrary to the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth:</hi> which thing he alſo did in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and many of the Saints did he ſhut up in Priſon, having received Authority from the chief Prieſts; and when they were put to death, he gave his voice againſt them. And he puniſhed them often in the Synagogues, and compelled them to blaſpheme; and being exceedingly mad againſt them, he perſecuted them even unto ſtrange Cities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57500:3"/>
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>He was deſcended from the Fathers and Mothers ſide of two Families of the greateſt Name and Note, ſome of them, in all <hi>Devonſhire;</hi> of one of them <note n="*" place="margin">P. 147. <hi>Clara &amp; perantiqua familia.</hi> Guillim's Diſplay of Heraldry, pag. 107.</note> 
                  <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in his <hi>Britannia</hi> doth record, that it is an Honourable and very Ancient Family; and of the other, <hi>Guillam</hi> in his <hi>Diſplay of Herauldry,</hi> mentioneth concerning one of that Name eſpecially, that his Merits do require, that, his Coat Armour ſhould be expreſſed in that ſelected manner of Blazoning, which is fitting to Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, in reſpect of his noble Courage and high Attempts atchieved, whereby he merited to be reckoned, The Honour of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and of Naval Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>He was born of Religious Parents, according to the meaſures of Light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in that Age, who gave him up to the LORD for the Miniſterial Office and Work; and accordingly he had his Education in the Families of Profeſſors of Religion; His Heart was enclin'd to love Books, and to delight in Learning from a Child; and he doth not remember that ever he gave way ſo much as to any on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> approving thought of ſtepping into any other Calling: Anſwerably unto this, he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by ſome of the ableſt Maſters of Grammar-Knowledg, and for ſome time was the higheſt of the Scholars in one of the moſt eminent Schools of all that County.</p>
               <p>About the beginning of the ſeventeenth year of his Age he was ſent to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to be skilled in the Arts and Sciences, in that corrupt unſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way and manner as then it was, and ſtill is; there he took two Degrees, tho little advancement he made in ſuch Scripture-Learning, as ſince through Mercy he has experienced to be found and uſeful: There he remained till the three or four and twentieth year of his Age.</p>
               <p>In this Time Univerſity-Wits had ſomewhat tainted and ſowred him with a bad Ferment, that he was ſomewhat ſwoln and prejudiced againſt the ſtrict Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion amongſt the <hi>Puritan</hi> Party, (the Land being then moſtly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into but Two Parties, <hi>Puritan</hi> and <hi>Prophane</hi>) though ſtill his Convictions, and the power of a Religious foregoing Education, ſecretly, held him in his retired ſerious conſiderate thoughts in ſome better liking with the way of a ſtrict holy Converſation even whilſt, rather than part with a witty Jeſt amongſt his <hi>Ingenioſo's,</hi> who were too much his Companions, he would have a fling at times at the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts;</hi> of whom he was no open Perſecutor, but gave vent unto ſome Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of another kind; of which more towards the cloſe about the Evidences of Grace. During this time he held on in the Common-Prayer-Book track, even to the expoſing of his Life to open danger, when Souldiers came in upon him with Swords and Guns, whilſt he was at his ſuperſtitious Worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 9. 3, 4, 5, 6. &amp; 22. 6, 7, 8. &amp; 26. 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gal. 1. 15, 16, 22, 23. Phil. 3. 7, 8, 9. 1 Cor 2. 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 11,——15.</note> He had a Miraculous Converſion; for, when he was in the heat of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Saints, being injurious to the Chriſtian Churches, and a Blaſphemer of God, of Chriſt God-Man, and of his Truths, Worſhip, Cauſe, Ways, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, ſuddenly there ſhined round about him a Light from Heaven; and he fell to the Earth, and heard a Voice ſaying unto him, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? And he ſaid, Who art thou, LORD? And the LORD ſaid, I am JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S whom thou perſecuteſt. It is hard for thee to kick againſt the Goads.</hi> And he trembling and aſtoniſhed, ſaid, <hi>LORD, What wilt thou have me to do? And the LORD ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, Ariſe, and go into the City, and it ſhall be told thee what thou muſt do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hiſtory of this wonderful Work he is now ready to own, and to declare before Princes, Prieſts, or People, where he had a Call and Opportunity; preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up that Chriſtian Doctrine and Diſcipleſhip, which but a little before he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perſecute down; counting all his former ſelf-righteouſneſs, formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhippings, creature-advantages, outward Church-priviledges, vain affectation of human wiſdom, by Philoſophic Studies, to be as dung, and as Dogs-meat, for the excellency of the Knowledg of Chriſt Jeſus his Lord, for whom he ſuffered the loſs of all things, that he might win Chriſt, and be found in him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not having his own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but, that which is through the Faith of Chriſt, the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith. And now he lays aſide
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57500:3"/> his old human Set-Forms, and prayed in the help of the interceding Spirit, Framing of ſuch arguing Requeſts within him as his preſent Caſe called for. Thus, he, who had been one of the prime of Sinners, is now become one of the greateſt Exal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers of the Father's rich Grace and free Love, of Chriſt's Alſufficient Satisfaction, and prevailing Interceſſion, and of the holy Spirit's powerful gracious working.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>The way and manner of the holy Spirit's working upon him hath been various at ſeveral times, yet in a marvelous gracious manner; even from his Childhood, and in his Youth, oftentimes by Terror, now and then by Bands of Love. He lay for many years under a ſpirit of bondage to Fear, being very often frighted in terrible Dreams, wherein he fell into deep Waters, the Earth ſliding away from under him, whilſt he endeavoured to climb up to the top of an Hill or Rock for ſafety, which he was not able to do: falling over Bridges into the Sea, and down from thence into the Gulph and horrible Pit (though at that time he little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that thus was the poſiture of the Creation as to the loweſt World.) The Devil many times ſeemed to be at hand, running to lay hold on him, though always he eſcaped, yet ſo terrified as awakened him, and left cold ſweats upon him: yet this kept him ſeveral years in aw, and held him back from many Sins. Once when he was tampering about one Sin, which was preparing for another Sin, though he did not then actually commit either the one or the other, a Voice with power ſmote his heart as with a Thunder-bolt from Heaven, <hi>What if God ſhould ſtrike thee dead and damned upon the place?</hi> which quickly ſent him to his private Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſet him about Praying, Reading, Confeſſing, Humbling work; and at other times he was put upon Faſting, thinking with himſelf to conquer Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Temptations, too much going forth in his own ſtrength, and depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Duties; which yet Experience told him were all too weak in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat without help from Chriſt and his Spirit. At other ſeaſons there were ſweet Allurings, eſpecially upon reading the Hiſtory of Chriſt's Life, Sufferings and Death, which did very much melt him into Tears, and kindly affect, and winningly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Heart.</p>
               <p>Though he dare not ſay, as one Miniſter told him concerning himſelf, he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A Self-Father, or, his own Spiritual Father; his meaning being, that he was his own Converter, begotten and born by that Word which he preached to others. If any would have <hi>Shem</hi> to name his Father, He, of and by whom he was born from Above, was <hi>Abi-jah, Jah</hi> my Father; <hi>Abi Ael,</hi> the mighty God, my Father: <hi>Abi-hu,</hi> He, and the Alone my Father He.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Shem</hi> has been in the loweſt World in his Spirit, in the Gulph, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in Hell; ſo alſo there have been two more remarkable paſſages at ſpecial ſeaſons when his Heart was taken into nearer union to, and cloſer fellowſhip with Chriſt in the uppermoſt World.</p>
               <p>The one was, when ſolemnly and ſeriouſly ſetting himſelf to enquire into the ſafety of his Spiritual Eſtate, he was held ſtrictly to theſe Terms, That he muſt burn his Papers with his own Hand, and his former Collections out of humane Authors of Philoſophical Learning, wherein much of that which was corrupt was heaped together, amongſt a little ſomewhat that was true and good: and that he muſt begin (as it it were) Religion, and all anew, and take all from Chriſt, and from his Word purely and only, with a Promiſe, That, then he ſhould be better taught, and not loſe any thing that was uſeful of what he knew before, and ſhould have a better and richer ſtock given in. About which time it was clearly revealed to him, and in him, by a paſſage in an Author, who ſo opened that word, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. The whole Scripture which the Engliſh Tranſlation doth render <hi>All Scripture,</hi> that for the whole and every part of his Religion, in all Doctrine and Duties, he muſt take the whole Scripture along with him, both Old and New Teſtament to be for him, where-ever the holy Spirit doth take occaſion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat of any ſuch particular ſubject-matter; which Word-Rule in the harmoniouſneſs and uniformneſs, or oneneſs of it throughout, has been of ſingular unexpreſſible uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him ever ſince in this Age of growing Light. This put him to a kind of offering up his <hi>Iſaac:</hi> But <hi>Jehovah,</hi> his <hi>Aelohim</hi> framed his Heart to it, and he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily anſwered the Call, and ſacrificed with his own hand in the Flames ſeveral
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57500:4"/> years Labours, of great value in the eſteem of ſome, (for he had ſtill an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mind, trying many ways of heaping up Learning, but was not ſet right till now.) And from that day to this he has found the LORD True, and Good as his Word, ſo that he can ſay, to the praiſe of this God of all Grace and Mercy, That ſcarce one week for many years has paſſed over him without ſome ſpecial Teachings, the holy Spirit opening ſome Scripture or other before him, and then opening the Eyes of his Underſtanding to take in the light and meaning thereof, of which he has gathered much, and it is laid up by him as his rich Treaſure in and under Chriſt: yea, it is a very black night and dark day with him, if there be any one ſuch whole natural day in any one week, wherein there is not ſomewhat of this: All the Glory be to <hi>Jehovah Aelohim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, how now? what ſhall be done to carry on Preaching and Praying Work? (for, he was a Teacher of others, who much needed to have been inſtructed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though he had a great Name amongſt Miniſters and People:) The Forms of Prayer were gone, the Fire had turned them into Aſhes. He had compoſed many of thoſe Forms of his own, upon ſeveral Caſes, with great variety; moſt Hearers could ſcarce diſcern it to be a Form of humane compoſure: but the LORD took him at his Word, and he muſt now truſt to the aſſiſtance and inworking of the Spirit of Grace and of Supplication, who has not been thus far wanting when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right depended on.</p>
               <p>About ſeventeen years ſince, when the <hi>Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> came forth, and the Profeſſion of <hi>Aſſent and Conſent,</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> were required, the LORD ſoon ſtated the Caſe, and reſolved the Queſtion upon <hi>Shem</hi>'s Mind and Heart, not ſo much as to touch that unclean Conſtitution of humanely invented Worſhip, and ſo he has continued ever ſince, a total thorow <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> though Afflictions and Perſecutions have abidden him from that time.</p>
               <p>After this the LORD honoured him with ſomewhat of a Viſion in the Spirit, wherein two of the choiceſt Revelations were made manifeſt to him and in him: For, in a very dark evening, whilſt a Priſoner, a little before his going to his Lodging, he bowing his knees in Prayer, was on a ſudden taken up in his Spirit as if he had been actually in Heaven, (This was about fourteen years ago, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering ſomewhat to that of <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 1,—4.</note>) where he had a clear view of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Glorified Humanity by an Eye of Faith, He ſitting in the ſides of the <note n="†" place="margin">Iob 23. 3, 4, 8, 9. &amp; 26. 6, 7. Pſal. 48. 1, 2, 3. &amp; 75. 6, 7. Iſa. 14. 9,—15.</note> North; which was as real to him as if he had converſed with Chriſt perſonally in the fleſh; and it is ſtill ſo, when he is in a right worſhiping Frame: being led to him as to the one Mediator and Advocate to carry on all his Affairs in the Court above. The other was <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 14. 1 Joh. 1 3, 7. Mat. 28. 19. John <hi>chap.</hi> 14, 15, 16, &amp; 17. 2 Cor. 3. 18. Pſ. 11 7. <hi>Their Faces,</hi> or, <hi>His Faces. (His,</hi> or <hi>their Aſpects.</hi> See <hi>Ainſworth in loc.</hi>) Numb. 12. 8. Heb. 6. 19. 20. &amp; 10. 19,—22.</note> A Self-evidencing view of thoſe Glorious Appearances of Father, Son, and holy Spirit, and diſtinctneſs of Communion with each of theſe in their ſeveral ſubſiſtences, ſhining forth in the Face of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> This ſight covered his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with ſuch a ſhining Light and bright Glory, that, their faces viewing him, was ſuch an heavenly Manifeſtation of unveiled Aſpects, as dwells with him to this hour, and is more or leſs in every ſolemn Duty of Inſtituted Worſhip, a guiding of his Spirit into that within the Veil, whither Jeſus the Fore-runner is for him entred. And this has been revealed to him to be his being baptiſed with the holy Spirit, <hi>Mat. 3. 11. Act.</hi> 1. 5. &amp; 11. 16.</p>
               <p>This Object raiſed him into an higher way of Later-Day-Glory-hymnifying, than his former way of ſinging by Mens Forms, read out of a Book, could reach unto. And thus it is through continuance of ſpecial Favour with him to this day, and will ever live with him; for, it eſpouſed and ſomewhat married his whole Man, Body, Soul and Spirit, to each of theſe Three in One <hi>Jehovah,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 54. 5. Pſa. 149. 2. Job 4. 17. &amp; 35. 10. Eccleſ. 12. 1.</note> as to his Husbands, Creators, and Makers; To the Father, as the Father; to the Son, as the Son; to the holy Spirit, as the holy Spirit; Makers, Husbands, Creators.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 26. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. Gal. 1. 1. Eph. 1. 1. &amp; 3. 7, 8. Act. 9. 15. Ro. 11. 13. 1 Tim. 2. 7. Gal. 1. 16, 17, 18.</note> He had ſuch a Call to the Office and Work of the Miniſtry as was not common; for he was an Apoſtle by the Will of God, and not of Men, neither by Men, but by Jeſus Chriſt; neither was the Goſpel, which was preached, of this Servant of Chriſt, according to Man; for he neither received it of Man, neither was he taught but by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57500:4"/> the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, who at that very time, when he ſo remarkably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>Paul,</hi> called him hereunto, ſaying to him, <hi>Ariſe, and ſtand upon thy feet; for I have appeared unto thee for this purpoſe, To make</hi> (or ordain) <hi>thee a Miniſter, and a Witneſs, both of thoſe things which thou haſt ſeen, and of thoſe things in which I will appear unto thee, delivering thee from the People, and from the Gentiles, unto whom I now ſend thee: To open their Eyes, and to turn them from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God: That they may receive Forgiveneſs of Sins, and an Inheritance amongſt them who are ſanctified by Faith, that is in me. Whereupon he was not diſobedient unto the heavenly Viſion, but ſhewed firſt unto them of</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>and at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and throughout all the Coaſts of</hi> Judea, <hi>and then to the Gentiles, that they ſhould repent, and turn to God, and do Works meet for Repentance.</hi> This preaching Office he preſently ſet about: <hi>Immediatly he conferred not with Fleſh and Blood, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther went he up to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to them that were Apoſtles before him, being</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 5. &amp; 12 11. Eph. 3 8. 1 Cor. 15. 8, 9, 10. &amp; 3. 5, 6, 7, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to the chief of the Apoſtles,</hi> yet calleth himſelf the <hi>leaſt of the Apoſtles,</hi> and an <hi>Abortive,</hi> and pronounceth himſelf unworthy to be ſaid to be an Apoſtle, becauſe he perſecuted the Church of Chriſt. He was but a Miniſter, by whom many of the People believed; yet appointed of God for thoſe great Ends, of bringing in of Sinners to Chriſt, and of building them up in Chriſt, that the LORD might have all the Glory, for <hi>Paul</hi> was not any thing in and of himſelf.</p>
               <p>The LORD wonderfully owning him, and bleſſing of his Labours, in ſuch large-ſpreading and deep-rooted Converſions, in planting of New-Teſtament-Churches, and many other ways; falſe Apoſtles, and others, envying and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him, do now call into <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 1. 2, 3. 2 Cor. 13. 3, 4, 5.</note> queſtion his Call to the Miniſterial Office and Work, whether it were lawful and right or not, becauſe it was not ſome way as theirs was, which they would have impoſed upon him, to which he could not ſubmit.</p>
               <p>This puts him upon making of an <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor, 9. 3.</note> Apology, to defend and magnify his Office, wherein if he were a Fool in glorying, if any ſo thought or judged him, it was chargeable on thoſe who ſo compelled him thereunto, that the Minds of young Converts might not be troubled, nor the Work of the Goſpel other ways hindred.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Arguments which, among others, he doth urge for the Proof of the Lawfulneſs of his Call, were drawn from his being <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 1. 15, 16. So was <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah;</hi> ch. 1. 5. So was <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> Luk. 1. 15, 16. So Chriſt, and ſo <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 49. v. 1, 5.</note> ſeparated thereunto from his Mother's Womb.</p>
               <p>He was eminently gifted by the Holy Spirit for this Office.</p>
               <p>He was much Graced by the ſame Holy Spirit for this Function.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">See before, <hi>pag. 6.</hi>
                  </note> He had a ſpecial Call thereunto by Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 1.</note> He had ſuch a Sight of Chriſt, and ſuch a Voice from Chriſt, relating to this, as was extraordinary.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 3, 4, 5. 1 Cor. 9. 12.</note> He had ſealing Teſtimonies from Heaven, in the Hearts of Multitudes, of his Miniſterial Call.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 14. 1, 2 3.</note> He had a Miracle-working Power communicated to him, for a further Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Lawfulneſs of his Call, and Truth of his Doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>His Call to this Office and Work of the Miniſtry, having ſomewhat in it which is outward, common, and ordinary, referring unto Men; and ſomewhat which is inward, ſpecial, and more than ordinary, relating unto God: it may therefore have ſome good Uſe, and profitable Tendency, to ſpeak diſtinctly unto each.</p>
               <p>That of it which refers unto Men is this: Let any almoſt plead and urge what they will or can, as to this, he has ſomewhat or other to ſay for the ſtopping of their Mouths; and all of it put together, is at leaſt more than he knows of any one Man, who juſtifies his Call from Men, can ſay for himſelf. Tho <hi>Shem Acher</hi> doth mainly and ultimately reſolve the Warrantableneſs and Rightfulneſs of his Call into ſomewhat elſe, as you will hear quickly, when his Caſe ſhall be compared with <hi>Paul</hi>'s, in ſeveral Particulars, as to the Miniſterial Office, wherein yet he doth give the Preheminence unto <hi>Paul;</hi> and this not only as to the degrees and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which were higher and larger, but alſo as to one or more of the kinds; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, as to <hi>Paul</hi>'s God-inſpiredneſs, and Infallibility, in being the Holy Spirit's
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57500:5"/> Penman of much of the Holy Scriptures, and ſomewhat elſe, which was then peculiar to his Apoſtolical Office, and Miracle-working Power.</p>
               <p>If thoſe who do place the Authority and Power in the Magiſtrate, to give a Call to the Miniſterial Office, ſhould queſtion <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s Call, he has by him to ſhew it under the Atteſts, the Hands and Seals of two Kings, and of one Protector; tho as to this laſt, and one of the other, they were other Men, who volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tarily of themſelves procured this for him, without his ſeeking.</p>
               <p>If thoſe who lodg this in Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, call upon him to give them ſome account of his Miniſterial Function, urging for a Succeſſion of lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Miniſters, ordained Ones, (beſides the extraordinary Prophets) Such were the Firſt-born of Families, from <hi>Adam</hi>'s time to <hi>Moſes, Exod. 19. 22, 24. &amp; 24. 5. Numb.</hi> 8. 5,—22. In <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Days it paſſed from the Firſt born unto <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, and unto the Tribe of <hi>Levi, Exod.</hi> chap. 28, 29. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 4,—10. Thus it continued all the Old Teſtament through. After the Jews return from the Babyloniſh Captivity, the Reformers ſought for the Sons of the Prieſts in the Regiſter, ſuch as were reckoned by Genealogy; thoſe who were not found ſuch, as polluted, were put from the Prieſthood, <hi>Ezra</hi> 2. 61, 62, 63: In the New Teſtament, there was <hi>John</hi> the Son of a Prieſt, honoured by the Prophecies of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Malachy;</hi> Chriſt ordained twelve Apoſtles, and ſeventy Diſciples, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Paul</hi> to the Office and Work of the Miniſtry; and they from Chriſt ordained others. As to this, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> has to ſay, that he has it to ſhew under the Hands and Seals of Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> for Deaconſhip, and for laying on of Hands, (who putting him to the queſtion, Whether he was perſuaded in his Heart, that the Holy Spirit called him to that Office? he anſwered, That he was ſo perſuaded) and of Biſhop <hi>Skinner,</hi> for the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>If ſuch as are for Ordination by a Claſſical Presbytery, (I meddle not here with that Controverſy, Whether a Biſhop and a Presbyter be both but one and the ſame Officer?) object againſt his Commiſſion, and if they ſhould take in Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, or Congregational Miniſters to join with them in the ſame Charge, he can return this, That he has the Approbation of a Dean, and of Canons, of Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Miniſters, both Presbyterian and Independent; alſo of Tryers in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector's Time, who were appointed for the examining, and the ſending forth of able fit Men to preach the Goſpel, and to take upon them the Care and Charge of Souls, tho he never was before them, neither did he apply himſelf unto them for ſuch an end, either by himſelf, or by others.</p>
               <p>If ſuch as do ſeat this in the Peoples Choice and Call, do reaſon the Caſe with him about it, that it muſt be received from them, as if the Power were originally there, he has much to offer unto ſuch to be conſidered by them. The People of that Pariſh where he lived before, refuſing to ſubmit to Church-Diſcipline, when, his Heart being ſet upon Reforming, according to what knowledg he then had, he propounded it to them; (for at that time he kept up a Meeting moſt Evenings, for ſometime, to ſpeak to ſome practical Caſe of Conſcience, and had written diverſe little Books of Diaries of his own Experiences.) They thus rejecting to be governed by the Laws of Chriſt's Houſe, hereupon Providence gave him as large, full, and clear a Call to one of the moſt populous Towns in all <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> by ſome Thouſands of that Town, and by Multitudes of other neighbouring Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereabouts, as any Miniſter in <hi>England,</hi> that he knows of, had in that Day. And after about two Years waiting by them, and referring the Caſe of Removal to them, into the Arbitration and Judgment of ſome Presbyterian Miniſters of other Counties, beſides the Encouragement of other Miniſters of the ſame County, both Presbyterian and Independent, who exhorted to, and approved of ſuch a Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val; he had as ſolemn an <note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2. 1. 19, 20. This Scripture was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Subject Matter of his firſt Sermon at his Entrance there.</note> Entrance into the taking charge of the People of that Town, as any Paſtor that he has heard of in that Age: For, beſides what hath been already mentioned, there was one ſolemn Day of Faſting kept publickly there, carried on by Presbyterians and others, in a great Aſſembly, to prepare that People, and to direct them in their Choice, where he was preſent, yet did not at that time, either as a Mouth from God in Preaching, or as a Mouth to God in Praying, openly appear. And afterwards, at another ſolemn Faſt there, on the Day of his Reception, when the Publick Work and Worſhip of that Day was performed by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57500:5"/> one Presbyterian Miniſter, and another Independant Miniſter, which was cloſed up by <hi>Shem Acher</hi> himſelf, and all to ſuch ſatisfaction and with ſuch rejoycing, of about two thouſand or more preſent, as that the Memory thereof, he ſuppoſeth, is ſtill kept alive in the Hearts of ſome hundreds of them.</p>
               <p>After this, about five years and half after, he being honoured with an Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Chriſt's ſake, for the Goſpel ſake, for Righteouſneſs ſake, for the Elect's ſake, he gathered a Church there in that place of Confinement, towards the end of which Impriſonment, upon a ſolemn Faſting day, ſo far as their light in thoſe matters did attain, the Brethren and Siſters then preſent thankfully owned their profiting under his miniſterial Labours, and gave a large Teſtimony to his miniſterial Office and Work; only this muſt be remembred, that, at ſeveral times upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral occaſions, he in the hearing of ſeveral of them, did always reſerve to himſelf the liberty of anſwering of Chriſt's Call to any other Place or People; for, he was the LORD's, having given up himſelf unto Him, to be wholy and only at his diſpoſe, and not to be during Life ſtaked down to any particular Place or People.</p>
               <p>Once more, ſince his coming to <hi>London,</hi> he has been gathering of another People; and that Church with whom he now walks, did all ſuch of them as were then actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Fellowſhip, upon a Solemn-Faſt-aſſembling, communicate their Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to one another, how much the LORD had bleſſed his Labours upon their Hearts, and towards the cloſe of the work of that day, (not by Impoſition of Hands, or Ordination to the miniſterial Office, or any thing of that Nature, which was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſo declared both by him and them.) One of them in the Name of the reſt, in Prayer to the LORD, did by ſtretching out of his Hands, as others alſo of them did, commend him unto the LORD in a ſpecial Meſſage to the Sabbath Churches in <hi>Wiltſhire, Hampſhire, Dorcetſhire, Gloceſterſhire,</hi> and <hi>Berkſhire,</hi> which was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by him, and proſpered with deſired Succeſs, the report whereof at his return, cauſed Joy to all the Brethren and Siſters in Fellowſhip.</p>
               <p>This is ſomewhat of that, which he here brings in as an Argument unto Men, who are urgent for ſuch outward, common, ordinary, Calls to this Office from Men.</p>
               <p>This was a choice piece of the Beauty of this Providence in this his age of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Light: For, let any one convinced of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, have been of what Judgment ſoever, yet ſtill there had been a Receiver of him into Church-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, whatſoever his Principle had been.</p>
               <p>If after all this, it be more deeply reſearched into, and he be cloſe and home put to it, what he himſelf doth mainly and ultimately reſolve his inward, ſpecial, more than ordinary Call into as to the miniſterial Office and Work; he deſireth, that, ſo far as the Caſe will run Parallel with <hi>Paul</hi>'s, (though he here, as before, gives the preheminence to <hi>Paul</hi>) it may be in a Brotherly manner and Chriſtian way admitted and received.</p>
               <p>He was ſet apart to this Office, from his Mother's Womb: For, his Father and Mother related to him, when he grew up to ſome capacity for the taking of this in, that, (if not whilſt he was in the Womb, in caſe he ſhould prove a Male perfect Child, yet at leaſt) upon his being born a Male Child with perfection of Limbs and of Parts, by Vow or ſome religious Promiſe made to God, they would give him up unto the LORD, to whom they dedicated him for the Office and Work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, which has ſince been ſuggeſted to him by the Holy Spirit, and confirmed by many Experiences according to the Word, which he doth embrace with a thankful joyful Heart, as a more than common Favour from that good Spirit. His Parents, as they had thus deſigned him to this ſpecial Courſe and honourable Calling; ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, they were at the care and coſt to train and breed him up in ſuch Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Learning, as the Principles and Attainments of that Age and Day dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them to. As he grew up, his ſtrong Propenſions, and continued Inclinations were for this Calling, as the only proper courſe of his Life intended for him; tho by invitation thereunto by his Father, and from others he has ſince diſcerned; that, he entered upon ſomewhat of it too ſoon and too unfurniſhed; for the longer he doth live, and the more ſpiritual diſcerning he hath, ſtill the more he ſees and feels of his <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16, 17.</note> Inſufficiency for ſo high, honourable, and great undertaking, and would gladly ſit at the Feet of others, every way more accompliſhed, and more <note n="†" place="margin">2 Chron. 24. 20. <hi>Margin.</hi>
                  </note> clothed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57500:6"/> with the Holy Spirit for it; and he is grieved at Heart, and afflicted in Spirit, to behold the over forwardneſs of ſo many in the preſent Age, who undertake to be publick Teachers of others, when divers of them do need to be catechizingly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught themſelves.</p>
               <p>Since his more thorow paſſing into this Office, the Holy Spirit, who doth divide his Gifts to every Man ſeverally as he will, hath in ſome meaſure <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ 68. 11. 18. Eph. 4. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> Gifted him for it: (which he would ſpeak thankfully, as acknowledging it to be meer Grace and ſpecial Favour; for, he aſcribes nothing of the Spirituallity of it to his own former Philoſophick Studies or ſelf Acquirements or human Inſtructing, but, it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Teaching, and Gifted infuſing from Heaven: ſo withal, humbly with ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abaſing, that, all this while he has made no further progreſs in a Fittedneſs and Ability for this Calling in the proper peculiar Endowments for it: though this he can ſay through Grace; that, for theſe laſt ſeventeen years, more eſpecially for the laſt fourteen years, he has had in the Strength and Supplies of the Holy Spirit, an induſtrious mind to trade with his Talent received; and there is ſeldom a day, wherein ſomewhat more is not, according to the <note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 25. 29. 1 Pet. 4. 10. Rom. 12. 3, 6. 1 Cor. 12. 3,-11. Luke 19 12,—26. 1 Cor. 7. 17.</note> Promiſe given unto him: and he remembers well, that, for about ſeventeen Years ago, though he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome knowledg of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Tongues before, yet this Meditation taking ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible hold of his Heart, that, when he went thorow the Bible, and examined the Gifts of Miniſters there, he could not find any one Miniſter of Chriſt lawfully called by him to that Office, who did not underſtand the Words of <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> in their Original Language; that which did ſo quicken him up to pray for, and to endeavour after a more growing Skilfulneſs, eſpecially in the inner knowledg of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Significations by the Holy Spirits Teachings, that, the ſerious Thoughts of, and unexpreſſible Advantages by, this Scripture Learning, do abide with him to this Day: and he doth judg it very requiſite for thoſe who conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rn themſelves in this Calling, to lay this more to Heart; had not the Holy Spirit ſomewhat Gifted him for this employ, he ſhould ſtill fear and doubt, he had never called him to it.</p>
               <p>The ſame Holy Spirit has in a meaſure Graced and Sanctifyed him for this Holy Function. This alſo as before concerning Gifts, he doth write with the ſame thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful humble Acknowledgments. It is not every one, who doth pretend and pride himſelf as Gifted, yea ſuppoſe him to have great common edifying Gifts, who is thereby preſently commiſſioned by Chriſt for the Miniſterial Office; ſeeing ſome ſuch are notoriouſly ſcandalous Livers, bitter Perſecuters of the Saints, open decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Enemies againſt the Power and Purity of right Worſhip, and of other true good Religion, againſt which they ſharpen and ſet the edg of thoſe Weapons of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg which they have: who, whilſt ſuch are ſo far from being to be admitted Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators of Church-Ordinances, that, they ought not to be admitted to, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in, a ſtate of Church-Memberſhip, but ſhould by the due regular exerciſe of Church Diſcipline, be ſhut or thruſt out from ſuch Communion. And here, when he duly conſiders, and ſeriouſly ponders, <note n="‖" place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 17. 1 Tim. 6. 11. 1 Sam. 9. 6, 7. Lev. 21. <hi>throughout.</hi> Ezek. 44. <hi>throughout.</hi> 1 Tim. 3. <hi>throughout.</hi> Tit. 1. 5,—9. Rev. 1, 2, 3. <hi>cha.</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 1,—4. Tit. 2. 1. Acts 6. 2,—4.</note> what Men of God, what chief Men among the People, how holy, how unblemiſhed, how unblameable, how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and vigilent, how temperate, how moderate, how ſound minded, how wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly circumſpect, how modeſt, how well behavoured, how fitly attired and well adorned, how hoſpitaliſh and harbourous in a courteous receiving and entertaining of Strangers, how apt, able, fit, appoſite to teach, well-habited and diſpoſed for orderly-clear-convincing-teaching; endued with a good Faculty of inſtructing and and of diſcipling of others, how not given to Wine-bibbing, or to Exceſs in any other Strong Drink which makes Drunk, not an Ale-ſtake, or common Tipler, not one that loves toſſing of Cups; not a ſtriker, ſmiter, or beater of others, not one of ungoverned heat, or of military Fierceneſs, not filthily-gaining, not cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly intent upon diſhoneſt baſe gain; how equal, full of Equity in all things: how, courteous, gentle, patient, how unbrawling either as to Speeches or Actions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining the offered occaſions of ſinful contendings: no lover of Silver nor Idolizer of Money: how well governing his own Family, Houſhold; having his Children (if the LORD give him any) in Subjection, under Diſcipline, in good order; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Children, not refractory, not obnoxious to the Sin of Luxury: not one who is but newly ingraffed or implanted in Chriſtian Profeſſion in God's Houſe, ſuch as ought to have a good Teſtimony from thoſe that are without, ſuch a one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57500:6"/> as cannot juſtly be called into queſtion, or into Court for any manifeſt Crime: what a Diſpenſer of God, as his Steward; not pertinaciouſly pleaſing of himſelf: not prone to anger, not haſty, not ſpirited for rage: what a lover of goodneſs, of good, both Men, Truths, and Things: how Juſt, how Holy, how Pious, how Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: how firmly adhering to that faithful Word which is according to wholeſom Doctrine, that ſo he may be able alſo to exhort in Doctrine, ſuch as is healthful and ſound, and to convince ſuch who are contradicting and gainſaying ones; not attending to Jewiſh Fables, or to Precepts of Men averſe from the Truth, or turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truth away, or turning from the Truth, one ſpeaking thoſe things, which do become ſound Doctrine; a Feeder of the Flock of God where he is: a carefully<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watchfully-overſeeing one, not forcedly, but willingly, freely, with a prompt or ready Mind; not imperiouſly domineering or lording it over thoſe allotted to his Care and Charge: being Exemplary to the Flock; one, who believeth and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for the Appearing of the chief Paſtor, to receive and carry away an unfading Crown of Glory: one, who gives himſelf to Prayer, and to the Word; whoſe Wife muſt be one who is honeſt, who proves conſtant, no Calamniatrix, not a deviliſh Slanderer, or falſe Accuſer, no malicious Detracter, one ſober, faithful in All: what a Star, what an Angel! When theſe Qualifications, and many more that might be added, are brought and put together, to meaſure, as by a ſtraight Rule, many of thoſe by, who lay claim to this Office, that doth put <hi>Shem Acher</hi> upon deep Sighing, and makes him ask this Queſtion in his Thoughts, Where do the able faithful Miniſters dwell?</p>
               <p>He has had ſome ſignal Calls to this Office by Chriſt, eſpecially at three times, one about fourteen years ago, another about ſeventeen years ſince, of both which an account has been given before for ſome other purpoſe, and once before both theſe, when with the former of theſe laſt two he did ſet himſelf, by Faſting and Prayer, to know the Mind of Chriſt, whether he had indeed ſet him apart to this Office: in all which times he had ſatisfying Anſwers, and Signs fulfilled quickly after in ſome remarkable returns by eminent Converſions.</p>
               <p>He has had ſuch a ſight of Chriſt in the North, as was clear and evident to his Eye of Faith, chiefly more at one Seaſon, mentioned before, which was made ſo real to him, and has more or leſs ſo continued for ſo many years Night and Day, as doth leave it out of doubt with him, in a degree, as if he converſed with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt himſelf, ſo far as <hi>Shem Acher</hi> in this ſtate of Imperfection, has a Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of walking with an exalted Chriſt in his ſtate of Glory.</p>
               <p>As for the Sealings on Earth, of his Commiſſion received from Heaven, in the Hearts of converted Sinners, of edifyed Saints, of comforted Souls, he had rather, others would ſpeak and declare than himſelf; however ſeeing ſomewhat may be expected from him, as to this Parrallel, he doth <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 14.—17.</note> give thanks unto God, who eſpecially for twenty years or more, has cauſed him to triumph in Chriſt, and has made manifeſt the favour of his Knowledg by him, more or leſs in every place, as he has travelled up and down with the bleſſing of the Goſpel of Chriſt. For, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome ownings of him and of his labours before whilſt he lived in a little Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh) when he was called to that Neighbour Town ſpoken of before, there was as hopeful a budding and blowing of young ones there and in the Neighbourhood, and he hopes much good brought forth to the praiſe of Grace in and by many; there being yet alive ſeveral ſcores who can, as he ſuppoſeth, ſomewhat ſenſibly call to mind the Truth of this: beſides what the LORD hath done by him in two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties during his Impriſonments for above nine years, at which time ſome were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten again in the bonds of the Goſpel; and alſo what good and gracious effects his preaching of the Goſpel has brought forth, by the Spirit and Bleſſing of God upon his Works ſince his Liberty, in any other place, particularly near and in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> For, <note n="†" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2. 19, 20.</note> what is his Hope or Joy or Crown of rejoycing? are not even a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, edifyed, comforted, confirmed People in the Preſence of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt at his coming? For, theſe are his Glory and Joy.</p>
               <p>As for a Miracle-working Power, ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> had, he doth not pretend to this, either for all the Kinds, or for thoſe high Degrees, and great Meaſures, as <hi>Paul</hi> was honoured withal: yet this he can ſay in Truth to the Glory of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, that his <hi>Aelohim</hi> hath done wonderful things
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57500:7"/> for and upon him, and marvellous Works by him for and upon others, as to heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cures both upon Spirit, Soul, and Body, and alſo as to the executing of very ſore threatned Judgments againſt and upon divers of his implacable Adverſaries: whereof there be Witneſſes, as to what was open and publick: the particulars whereof would make this Narrative too long: only one Experience he ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, which was a great ſecret of the LORD Chriſt's uſing him as his Adminiſtrator upon himſelf. Having, by much labour in his work in the forementioned Town about twenty years ſince, broken his Strength, which cauſed a Rupture, he uſed ſuch means for a Cure, as the moſt skilful Phyſician, and ſome others moſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in ſuch caſes could help him to, all which proved ineffectual; whereupon his Thoughts were inwardly at work, upon this Enquiry, whether there were not ſome other way for his Cure to be ſought after? This was brought upon his Heart, that, <note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 5.</note> the Ordinance of Anointing the Sick had not been uſed: he was convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the need and uſe of this Ordinance, of the ſtanding preceptive and promiſing part of it; but, knew not whither to his ſatisfaction to go, or ſend for a right Adminiſtrator, the Miniſters generally in thoſe parts at that time, eirher not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Light or Faith therein, and ſome of them openly oppoſing of it: hereupon a ſecret Voice whiſpers, that, as a Meſſenger from Chriſt, he ſhould adminiſter it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, the caſe being ſo circumſtanced; which accordingly he did, and felt the healing ſtrengthning Effect of it quickly: which has continued for many years, ſo that, he knows not, but, that <note n="†" place="margin">Joh. 3. 25, 26, 27.</note> Sanative Virtue having been drawn down from Chriſt, by a touching of him, by the Hand of Faith, in a way of believing on him and on his Word, he is well healed, though ſtill under and for Chriſt he uſe apt means for the continuance of this great Mercy in order to Service: all the praiſe be to him for his Mercy, and for his Truth.</p>
               <p>So that what <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt ſaid in the ſame caſe, both as to his Baptiſm and Miniſtry, <hi>A Man can receive nothing, except it be given him from Heaven, Shem Acher</hi> doth apply to his own Caſe, who hath not in this Matter, ſo far as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance here doth anſwer, taken what is lawful and good, but what has been given unto him thus from above. In the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> or Suppoſition, that one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Argument or Matter upon which <hi>John</hi> was then diſputing, thoſe Words are referred to what went immediatly before, relating to the Miniſterial Office of Chriſt, or of <hi>John,</hi> or of both, as to Teaching and Baptizing: Both <hi>John</hi> the Miniſter, and Chriſt the Maſter, having received Gifts, Graces, and a Call from Heaven to exerciſe this honourable Function, or delegated Employment; they both having been owned and dignified with a Divine Teſtification from above, which gave and confirmed them in their lawful Authority ſo to act, (<hi>Mat. 21. 25. John</hi> 1. 23. &amp; 3. 11, 25, 26, 27, 32, 33.) Theſe right Words, altho more generally laid down, have great force of ſtrong Reaſon, and of convincing Argument in them, to prove, That a Man can receive nothing, take nothing to himſelf, as to ſuch a Call and Office, and the Execution thereof, in a regular way, and right manner, by due Commiſſion, and warranting Authority, except it were firſt given him from Heaven: For tho legitimately to give, and legitimately to receive, are related to each other, and ſo are together at once; yet in order, to give is firſt: And therefore tho the Verb be in the Preſent Tenſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3 <hi>Sing. Praeſ. Subj.</hi> yet the Participle is in the paſt Time, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Partic. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut. Praet. Paſſ. Not any,</hi> no Man of right good Conſcience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 4. is to take this Honour to himſelf, but he who is called of God, ordained and appointed thereunto by his Word-Warrant, (<hi>Numb. 16. 10. 1 King. 13. 33. Luke 3. 2. Acts 23. 5.) Not any taketh:</hi> As to the matter of Right none can juſtly take, none ought to take; tho many as to matter of Fact have taken, and do take, without Gift from <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> the great Lord over all. It being a Function of Divine Inſtitution, and of ſpecial Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, of great Honour, and of weighty Charge, both ordinary and extraordinary Miniſters muſt be able to prove their Call, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 4. &amp; 3. 2. <hi>Jer 17. 16. Amos 7. 15. Rom. 1. 1. 1 Pet. 1. 1. 1 Tim. 4. 14. Epheſ. 4. 11. Exod. 28. 1. 2 Chron. 13. 9, 10. 1 Cor. 12. 28, 29. 1 Sam.</hi> 23. Where any have upon their own Heads ſet themſelves a running, or have been puſhed forwards by others, whom the Lord never ſent, it concerns them to conſider how they will anſwer it.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57500:7"/>
               <p>And this is one Ground and Reaſon for this preſent <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 3.</note> Apology, which is an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer with a Defence as to Men's falſe chargings, <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> wherein he can juſtify himſelf and plead his Office in their Day and Court, though in ſome particular Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Caſe, the Searcher of Hearts, and the Tryer of Reins, can find matter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough againſt him for which to condemn him: O how much Wiſdom and Love has the righteous Judg manifeſted towards <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> in that he has found out a way, wherein to juſtify him from that wherein he can and doth comdemn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</p>
               <p>He has patiently born the ſecret Artifices, and open Attempts of ſome to defame him and to decry his Miniſtry for about theſe ſix years laſt paſt, as being made wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deny himſelf, to take up his Croſs dayly, and ſo to follow Chriſt: but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving long obſerved, that ſuch do ſtill trouble the minds of divers, who have been hopefully coming on, and do lay ſtumbling-blocks in the way for the hinderance of others, whereby Goſpel-work has been at a ſtand, the Sabbath Cauſe wronged, many Souls prejudiced, and the Honour of our LORD at leaſt darkned, to ſay no more, he doth now judg it high time (having had ſeveral louder Calls there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto of late) to do publick and open right to this Cauſe (and to ſome other after Cauſes and Caſes) where others have done it ſuch publick and open wrong, which is but an act of warrantable regular love towards himſelf and towards others: and alſo an act of due Equity, and of diſtributive Juſtice, for the wiping off of unkind Calumnies and injurious Aſperſions imputed and caſt upon an honourable Office; about which he hath been many and many a time <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 18. 13</note> prejudged and condemned (as alſo in other caſes) before his Matters of Fact and of Right have been known, or he himſelf heard; thus has his ſilence in this cauſe been miſinterpreted a confeſſion of Guilt. If any ask, why this had not been brought forth ſooner, he has much to ſay in anſwer, if he would enlarge: but in ſhort, ſome hints he has already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which carry forcibleneſs of right Words in them, to the impartially intelligent and ſpiritually diſcerning; and he hoped, that, the Experiences of many in this City, upon whoſe Hearts the LORD had ſealed to the Office of his Miniſtry, might have put ſome timely ſtop to the further ſpreading of ſuch defameings. Beſides, it is evident to him, being led far into the myſtery and meaning of this Providence; that, this is the fitteſt ſeaſon for the making of the preſent Apology: and, if, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome will charge him with Vanity and Pride, with Folly and Vain-boaſting, in writing ſo much upon his own Defence, or, if it have another effect than many are well aware off, for the putting of ſeparate Churches upon a further ſearch into the Scriptures of Truth, about the right conſtituting of Churches, the lawful Call to the Miniſterial Office and Work, and ſome other weighty Ordinances, ſpoken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in this Paper, it will much concern thoſe, who make the exception duly to ponder, who is chargeable, Whether the Apologiſt, who in a Cauſe and Caſe ſo circumſtanced doth make his honeſt Defence and juſt Plea? or, thoſe unfriendly ones, who have compelled him hereunto? which advocating for Innocence, ſo far as it is Innocence, has Scripture-Warrant <note n="†" place="margin">Joh. 29. and 31. Chap. and elſewhere in that Book. Acts 22. and 26. chap. 1 Cor. 4. 1.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. and 2 Cor. 11. throughout, and 12. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> both in the Old and New Teſtament; ſo that, if he have been a Fool in glorying, they are others who have neceſſitated him thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 19. 18. and 22. 16. 1 Cor. 1. 13.—17.</note> He was baptized upon this eminent Converſion, and clear Call to the Office and Work of the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>He being ſent more to Preach the Goſpel, than to Baptize, though this were in his Commiſſion too. They were not very many whom he did Baptize, leſt any ſhould misjudge that he had baptized in his own Name, which he doth expreſly deny and diſown. He is called upon not to tarry, but to ariſe, and baptiſing to be baptized, and waſh away his Sins, calling on the Name of the Lord; whereupon he doth ſubmit to this Baptiſmal Ordinance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>He having had ſuch Calls, and ſuch clearings up of this Call, to this Miniſterial Office, of which ſo large an Account has been given, eſpecially at thoſe ſolemn
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57500:8"/> Seaſons of Faſting and Prayer, when he ſet himſelf more in ſerious earneſt to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied concerning this his Call from Heaven, by the Holy Spirits leaving ſome ſealing Teſtimony thereof upon his Heart, according to the Word, at ſuch a needful time, when he was under ſome perplexing Doubts and diſtreſſing Fears, about this Call. Being thus prepared for it, as is already rehearſed, the Light of (amongſt ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) two Truths and Duties of this Age were evidently made known unto him, the one of the Seventh-day weekly Sabbath, the other of perfecting Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm (he doth leave others here, whoſe Caſe at preſent is, or hereafter may be more concerned in this Matter, if it be not already perfected upon and in them, to conſider, whether then, if there be otherways a fittedneſs for, and a Call to, the Miniſterial Function, it may not be proper and uſeful to enter upon this Office with ſuch <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 6. 1, 2. Mat. 3. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. and 4. 1.—17. Act. 9. 18, 20. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d 26 16.—20. Exod. 29. 4. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8. 6.</note> perfecting of Baptiſm now they are grown Believers? ſo were the Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament, (which is mentioned not at all to reinforce any Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Shadow, Figure, Type, or Ceremony, now under the preſent New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament Adminiſtration of Grace) ſo was Chriſt; ſo were his Apoſtles: ſo was <hi>Paul,</hi> let the Spirit of God from his Word ſpeak with Men's Hearts about this. I forbear in this place, to add any further Arguments for, or Advantages by, this.)</p>
               <p>The occaſion of his paſſing into the Scripture-Path, of the weekly ſeventh-day-Sabbath was this: A near and dear Brother, and Friend of his from the Country, wrote this Caſe of Conſcience to him; whether, the firſt day of the Week, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly obſerved by almoſt all Chriſtians, or the ſeventh, which is the laſt day of every Week, in the weekly returns of it, were indeed the weekly Sabbath, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God's Command? or in words to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me effect, for it is now about ſixteen years ſince; and he earneſtly deſired the Opinion and Judgment of <hi>Shem Acher</hi> upon this Caſe. Upon the Receipt of this Letter, he was ſomewhat ſtartled at this new Propoſal, though he was not ſo fully ſatisfied for ſome years before about any word-Inſtitution, for obſerving the firſt day (as a Siſter in Sabbath-Fellowſhip, conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under his Miniſtry, a ſhining Ornament to her holy Profeſſion, whilſt here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but now above with the LORD, informed and reminded him, that, when ſhe propounded the very ſame Caſe to him about ſix or ſeven years before, he gave her a very faint unſatisfactory anſwer, as if he ſcarce were then a cordial Favourer of that firſt day; for, tho he preached up Sabbath-Duties and Priviledges in that Town, yet his Aſſiſtant was, as one part of his Work, to engage in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, which was the limitted day.) At the firſt receipt of that Caſe, he was full of other work and employ, about his own and other Caſes, and laid it aſide for near a Month; the Brother whoſe Spirit was tender in this Caſe, as in many other new Caſes, ſent a ſecond Letter, with renewed importunity, requiring and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting a ſpeedy Anſwer; Upon this, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> ſpeaks to <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Spirit, to Chriſt God-Man, in Prayer about it, and then makes Scripture-Teſtimonies to be <note n="†" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 24.</note> the Men of his Counſel: and being under an Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to take the whole Scripture along with him, for the reſolving and determining of this Caſe, and to lay aſide all his former Apprehenſions, and no longer to parle with Humane Traditions, Philoſophical arguings, Carnal reaſonings, or any other unſcriptural Authorities, he took his Bible, which he has now had about forty years, and to which he was well uſed, and ſo could with the more readineſs turn unto apt places, beginning with the firſt Week of the created World, and there he found that, <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 2, 3.</note> the weekly Seventh-day-Sabbath had Foundation, both in <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Word, and in Created Nature, as being the only day of the whole Week, on which the Creator and Redeemer reſted, which day he Bleſſed, and which day he Sanctifyed, for Sabbath-Purpoſes and Priviledges, and not any other Day of the Week, neither firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, nor ſixth, but only the ſeventh. On he goes with his enquiry through the whole Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and finds the ſeventh day Sabbath <note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 16. 22.—30.</note> reinforced, and the neglect and profaneing thereof reproved, before the ſolemn proclaiming of it at Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> where the very next ſtep in his Travails he hears <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 19, and 20 <hi>chap. parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly chap. 20. verſ. 8, 9, 10, 11.</hi>
                  </note> the trumpeting promulgation of this Kingly Law of the Seventh day Sabbath, ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loud in his Ear and Heart: and ſtill, the further he paſſed on in the after Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Prophets, the more he is led along in the Seventh-day-Sabbath-way, till he came full home to the cloſe of the Old Teſtament, with this Seal put upon this Scripture-Canon or Rule by <hi>Jehovah</hi> himſelf, <note n="†" place="margin">Mal 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember ye the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57500:8"/> Law of Moſes, my Servant,</hi> all and every, both of the Commands for keeping holy of the weekly Sabbath day, and of the Promiſes of Bleſſings and Sanctifyings of week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sabbath day to right Obſervers of it, and alſo of the Threatnings denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Profaners of the weekly-Sabbath-day, relating only to the ſeventh, the laſt day of every week, and to no other day of the week. He was now in a ſhort ſpace of time, the very ſame day of entering upon this enquiry, got ſo far forwards in this way, of the ſeventh-day Sabbath from that Light and Truth which <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> ſent forth from his word by his Holy Spirit, that, he forthwith concluded, there was no either going back, or ſtepping aſide, for him out of this Scripture-Path: For, if all the Old Teſtament were for it, the New was not againſt it, ſeeing if any had preached up the firſt, or any other day, except the ſeventh, of the whole week, at the beginning of the New Teſtament-diſpenſation of Grace, thoſe who were more <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 17. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> noble-raced Believers on, and Diſciples of Chriſt, before the Writings of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, who ſearched the Scriptures they then had, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the firſt-day-pretended-Sabbath-Doctrine were true or not, they could not find that written Word, which they then enjoyed, had any ſuch Inſtitution at all in it, but, the weekly Sabbath's <note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 25. 11, 16, 21, 22. 1 Kings 8. 9. Jam 2. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> crowning honour was all through viſible and legible upon the head of the ſeventh day only. However he narrowly examined, and diligently compared the whole New Teſtament Writings by the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles: and there he ſoon diſcovered, that, the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 21. 1 Cor. 11. 1. 1 Joh 2. 4, 6. and 4. 17.</note> Example he was to follow in all the Acts of Decalogical Obedience, or Obedience to the Laws of the ten Words, and whoſe exact perfect Holineſs and Righteouſneſs both of Nature, Heart, and Life was fully every way anſwering to all the demands of this Law, which was to be both imputed to Believers for their Juſtification, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to by Believers in their Sanctification; this Chriſt all his Life long, in the weekly returns of the Sabbath, kept the <note n="†" place="margin">Luk. 4. 16,—31. &amp; 23 56. &amp; elſewhere.</note> ſeventh day Sabbath, and no other day of the week as ſuch, to which the Goſpels give abundant Teſtimony. Now he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be more confirmed, and wondereth how he could ſo much overlook, ſo ſelf-evidencing a Truth and Duty ſo long: he converſeth further with the Records of the Apoſtles, whether their Doctrine and Practice did Harmonize, and tune in the ſame Concord with this new <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 92. Title. Jer. 6. 16. &amp; 17. 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Song, Pſalm, and Hymn of the true good old weekly ſeventh day Sabbath. His only remaining work now left, was to conſult the Apoſtles Writings, and therein he reads in plain legible Characters, that, as Chriſt's Cuſtom, Manner, or conſtant practiſed Uſage was; ſo alſo was <note n="†" place="margin">Luke 4. 16. Acts 17. 2, 3. &amp; 18. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi>'s (the Expreſſion is one and the ſame in the <hi>Greek</hi>) to obſerve the ſeventh-day as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weekly Sabbath day, and that, no other day in the whole week has both the Name and Nature of a weekly Sabbath-day given to it by the Holy Spirit, but only the ſeventh day: and that Obedience to theſe Laws of Chriſt is ſo often called for both <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 5, 6, 7. <hi>chap.</hi> Joh. 14. 15. Luk. 10. 25, 26, 27, 28. Rom. 4. 15. &amp; 5. 13. &amp; 13. 8, 9, 10. Jam. 2. 8, 9, 10, 11, 13. Heb. 5. 9. Rev. 12. 17. &amp; 14. 12. &amp; 22. 14, 15, 18, 19.</note> by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as an evidence of Love to Chriſt, and of other Intereſt in him, as a Saviour; and that the new Teſtament Scripture was alſo clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up with Chriſt's Seal of Bleſſing to thoſe who doing theſe his Commandments, and of pronouncing a Sentence of Excommunication againſt any Man, who ſhould either add to, or take from this written Word, Will, and Law of Chriſt. The whole Scripture being thus profitable for this Doctrine and Duty of the weekly ſeventh day Sabbath, Chriſt ſate as one expecting an anſwer, readily, heartily, whereupon <hi>Shem Acher</hi> was not diſobedient to this heavenly Teaching by the Holy Spirit; but reſolves in the ſtrength and ſupplies of the ſame good Spirit, to ſet about the Practice of it; and this State of the Queſtion he ſends to his enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Brother, who alſo forthwith embraced the ſame Truth, and reduced it to Practice.</p>
               <p>And now lo, a very formidable Sight ſtares him in the Face; for he ſaw ſuch an Army of Oppoſers, not only profane, but profeſſing, not only Foes, but Friends, all almoſt as one Man up in Arms againſt him, as ſoon as it ſhould take Air abroad, (for he was then the LORD's Priſoner) and be known, that it was his Principle<note place="margin">† Pſ. 119. 165<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> and Practice. He alſo foreſaw, that tho this was no * Stumbling-block at all to him, neither any diſturbance to his own great Peace; yet many others would throw it as a Stone of Offence in their own and others ways, to the troubling the Minds of young Ones. In ſuch Multitudes, who promiſed ſo fairly, and came on ſo towardly, how many were likely to be much prejudiced
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57500:9"/> againſt him, and his former and after-Miniſtry? And what was moſt terrible of all, <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 28. 22.</note> how evil (tho injuſtly) many were likely to ſpeak againſt the Word and Ways of the LORD, and to blaſpheme <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s fearful, glorious and holy Name. Chriſt ſtill held him to former Terms, of bringing All to an whole Chriſt, and his whole Word; and ſuitably the good Spirit framed his Heart to this holy Reſolve, Duty is mine, the Iſſues and Succeſſes of things are the LORD's, and do belong to him.</p>
               <p>He privately obſevred the Seventh-day-Sabbath for ſome time, but with great Difficulties, and ſore Trials, and diſtreſſing Hardſhips in the Priſon: He imparts the LORD's Teachings of him to one, and then to another privately, who gave place in them to this Word-Truth and Law; and ſo unto ſome others, as they were capable of receiving it. And when four or five were hopefully gained over, he could hold no longer, and could not but ſpeak the Truths and Things of Chriſt in a more open Declaration, and publick Profeſſion; which being underſtood by ſome Miniſters and others, two Miniſters came to him in the Priſon, a little before the end of the ſixth day, with vehement earneſt importunate deſirings, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and entreatings, and other arguings and charmings, that, he would forbear, tho but one day, the next day, which was the ſeventh day, to conſult and conſider of ſo weighty a matter, in ſo great a change for one week, Oh for one week longer! His Anſwer was quick; ſhort, full, and reſolved, in the Strength of the LORD, No, he would not put it off one day more, it was clear as the Light to him through the whole Scripture, and if he ſhould put away from him this Statute of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> tho but for one day, he knew not, but that the Holy Spirits quicknings, teachings and comfortings of him, might withdraw, and Convictions be darkened and deadned: From this time, tho Sufferings for Chriſt came on, yet Conſolations by Chriſt did abound, and the Scriptures did look with a clearer Face; ſuch is alſo the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of many others, who are upright-hearted walkers with Chriſt, and thorow followers of Chriſt in this way of his Command. The very next day, therefore, the ſeventh day, he celebrated as the weekly Sabbath day, openly witneſſing to it, and publickly declaring for it, from the Word: remembring, <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 18. 37.</note> that of his LORD Chriſt, <hi>To this end was I born, and for this cauſe came I into the World, that, I ſhould bear witneſs unto the Truth; every one that is of the Truth, heareth my Voice.</hi> This was the ſaying of Chriſt himſelf a few hours before his Death. Since that, <hi>Shem</hi> never met with any Objection, that could ſhake or ſtagger him, but all wrought for his fuller Confirmation and Eſtabliſhment.</p>
               <p>In the next place, his perfecting of Believers Baptiſm comes to be conſidered. Convictions about this alſo, did quickly ſpread in the Priſon, and from thence in other places. Having no convenient Accommodations for Dipping, under cloſe Confinement, he and two more took up Reſolutions to paſs under that Ordinance, when the LORD ſhould give his Priſoner Liberty: when he was ſet free, he and the other being at a time in <hi>London,</hi> two Brethren and one Siſter, being throughly ſatisfied in each other, took Boat and rowed down to <hi>Batterſey</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> and having diſcovered a convenient place of paſſing into the <hi>Thames</hi> River, intended there to ſubmit to this Appointment of their LORD the next Morning, if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented or hindred. There they kept Sabbath: before the ending of which day, ſomewhat providentially fell out by a difference in Judgment, which did put a ſtop to that whole Action for that time. Thus the LORD wiſely ordered, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly over-ruled this Affair for Good.</p>
               <p>For he, having before been wrought off from all other whatſoever, to bring all entirely to an whole Chriſt, and to his whole Word, to Him and to it only, had the fairer and fuller opportunity to conſider before hand, how it might be done in the pureſt way, and to compare what he could meet with afterwards, if it might tend to his clearer Inlightning, or further Eſtabliſhment; that no one Mark of the Beaſt might be found upon him at Chriſt's coming to Glory.</p>
               <p>Before, he therefore writes downright to the Caſe for matter of Fact, he will ſet down, what both before and ſince, he hath met with for an anſwer to this Queſtion, <hi>Who ſhould be the Adminiſtrator, and who is fitteſt for it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were divers of the Perſwaſion and Practice for Believers Baptiſm, ſome who had been his Fellow Priſoners, others of the ſame mind who gave him Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57500:9"/> Viſits: but, his Spirit was not ſatisfied with any one of them. For, as for the Objection that has been made, that, a dead Man cannot bury himſelf, as if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a Man could not baptize himſelf: Such arguing from ſome Similitudes are often miſtaken and miſapplyed, and recoil upon the Objecter. As in this Caſe, a grown Believer, if in any circumſtanced Caſe he have a ſufficient Call to baptize himſelf, yet is ſuppoſed to be not altogether dead, but, alive both in Nature and in Grace too: and a living Perſon may do ſuch an Action, as may ſet out a dying, burial, and riſing again. Let a Swallow ſpeak in this Caſe; <note n="†" place="margin">See <hi>Swan's Spaeculum Mundi,</hi> p. 408.</note> Hiſtory writes of this Bird, that, in the beginning of Autumn, it gets among the Canes or Reeds, where it ſinks it ſelf into the Waters, thus dying and burying it ſelf, and at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Spring it riſeth up alive again. Being in <hi>London,</hi> and making enquiry there, his diſatisfaction grew on: For, upon ſearch made concerning, either a Firſt-or-After-Adminiſtrator of this Ordinance, he was informed, either by printed Records, or by credible Witneſſes, that the Adminiſtrator, was,</p>
               <p>Either, a Self Baptizer; ſuch he knew not one lawfully authorized thereunto: (which yet) he will not totally condemn, eſpecially, if a Call can be cleared up thereunto from the LORD. The Grounds and Reaſons whereof are not fit to be brought in here, particularly, tho the diſcerning Reader may catch at Hints enough in what doth follow. There are <hi>Hebrew</hi> words, which do ſet out ſome ſuch Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that are in two Conjugations, one of which Conjugations, <hi>Hithpahel,</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo, and the other Paſſive in <hi>Niphal</hi> is often, ſignificantly <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Such as <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chatz,</hi> and <hi>Hithrachatz, Nibtal. Niſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph. Shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph.</hi> Heb. 9. 10. Lev. 15. 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gen. 17. 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rom. 4. 11. Col. 2. 1, 2. In the <hi>Greek</hi> a Paſſive Verb, has often an Active ſignification. See for this <hi>Paſor</hi>'s Greek Sacred Grammer of the New Teſtament, <hi>p.</hi> 147, 148, 149. in many Scripture-Inſtances. Thus alſo in the <hi>Latin</hi> there are divers Verbs, which are called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſuch as Paſſively do work Actively upon a Man's ſelf. See <hi>Daneſius</hi> his <hi>Paralipomenae.</hi> p. 78, 79, 80, 81, 82, 83.</p>
                     <p>In the <hi>Greek,</hi> Words of the Middle Voice have often an Active ſignification, ſometimes a Paſſive, now and then both.</p>
                     <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 3 <hi>Plur. aor. 1 Med.</hi> They baptiſing (themſelves) were baptized in the Cloud and in the Sea: Thus it was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Types, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſanctifying by the Word and Prayer, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> went in and under of themſelves. Thus, <hi>Act. 22. 16 <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, aor. 1. Imper. Mood</hi> baptizing (thy ſelf) be thou baptized. <hi>Shem Acher</hi> will not ſay, there was nothing at all of this ſelf-baptiſing by Chriſt's appointment upon himſelf, tho he reſolves it into the Act of another, of Chriſt himſelf, upon him, he being the princiipal Baptizer of him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 16. The deeper reſearch that <hi>Shem Acher</hi> doth make into this Scripture, the more Note-worthyneſs doth he ſee in it. There are two Verbs in it, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, both of them relating to one and the ſame thing; that is, to Baptiſmal Waſhing, and they are both of them of the ſame middle Voice, of the ſame Imperative Mood, derived from the ſame firſt Aoriſt, of the ſame Number, of the ſame Gender, and of the ſame Perſon, and therefore both according to conſenting Scripture, and in right Reaſon, ſhould have the ſame ſignification, either Active, or Paſſive, or both Active and Paſſive; let it then and therefore be here minded and conſidered, that, whatever of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Significancy the latter of them may have in part, as the ſame Verb of the ſame middle Voice has in another Mood, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. which muſt be made up by the ſupply of ſome Prepoſition hereof <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſaith <hi>Piſcator,</hi> which is wanting, and muſt be put before the Accuſative Caſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, waſh thou off according to, or concerning of becauſe for, or by reaſon of thoſe Sins of thine; yet ſtill at leaſt mainly according to Grammar-Syntax and Propriety, it muſt be Active here; and ſuch a Syntax is found in other Authors, particularly in <hi>Homer, Iliad. σ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>————<gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quàm celerrime Patroclum abluerent a ſanie ſanguinolentâ.</hi> So that, the foregoing Verb alſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, is to be allowed the like Active meaning, in this place, Baptize thou, (thy ſelf, and others, Chriſt putting baptiſing into <hi>Paul</hi>'s Commiſſion, as one part, tho not the principal part of his Miniſterial Office.) It is gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ted, that, the ſame Verb, referring to the ſame Baptiſm, in the Paſſive Voice, has a Paſſive Signification, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 18. which Paſſive Voice it often Reflexive, that is Actively-Paſſive: However, in <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 16. all the words of the Verſe do carry an Active Sence with them. God can make a Man, eſpecially a Miniſter, an Active Adminiſtrator of an Ordinance, and upon himſelf, ſo it is in that other Ordinance of the Supper.</p>
                     <p>Thus, in the <hi>Syriack,</hi> the one Verb here in this place Active, the other Reciprocal and Reflexive. <hi>Pegnil, Ith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pegnal,</hi> and <hi>Ithpagnal,</hi> are much after the Uſe and Form of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Conjugation <hi>Hithpahel,</hi> which doth ſignify the Action of one upon himſelf, ſuch an Action as is Reflected on its own Subject; for which cauſe the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians do generally affirm, that, this Conjugation doth want a Paſſive Form. <hi>Conjugatio haec parens eſt &amp; proles;</hi> and ſo, it is ſometimes rendred, 2 Sam. 20. 10. <hi>Cavet ſibi.</hi> Gen. 49. 1. <hi>Congregate vos.</hi> Iſa. 52. 2. <hi>Excute te.</hi> Luk. 13. 24. <hi>Cavete vobis.</hi> Iſa. 29. 9. <hi>Cogitabundi eſtote.</hi> Act. 9. 26. <hi>Ad adjungendum ſe.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in <hi>Daniel</hi> and in <hi>Ezra, Hith,</hi> is in ſome of thoſe Scriptures uſed for, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Aith,</hi> in the <hi>Chaldee</hi> and <hi>Syriack.</hi> If any after all this will alledg, that <hi>Ananias</hi> did baptize <hi>Paul;</hi> when they have firſt, if they can, make it clear, convincing, and evident, that he did ſo, let them bring forth ſuch an <hi>Ananias,</hi> who has an expreſs immediate Call by a Voice from Chriſt out of Heaven, confirmed alſo by a Miracle wrought, that, he has ſuch a Call and Commiſſion thereunto, and <hi>Shem</hi> doth purpoſe to conſider of it.</p>
                  </note> Reflective both Active and Paſſive upon a Man's own ſelf: And there being ſome Typical Baptiſms by the Inſtitution of <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> in the Old Teſtament; as alſo another Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57500:10"/> of the ſame Inſtitution, which has much the ſame Significancy with Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even Circumciſion, which doth denote the mortification and putting off of the ſinful body of the Fleſh through the Circumciſion of Chriſt, being buried toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him in Baptiſm, the Sign and Seal whereof <hi>Abraham</hi> at the firſt paſſing into it, did both actively and paſſively adminiſter from the LORD upon himſelf, by the cutting quite away the Fleſh of the Foreskin; and Circumciſed the reſt of the Males in his Family: of which no more at preſent, till Controvertiſts leave their heats of Paſſion in contending and grow cool, and become Men of Underſtanding, of a more excellent Spirit.) But, he knew no ſuch Adminiſtrator to his ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For, if the Hiſtorian have not wronged ſome of the firſt ſo baptized in <hi>Holland,</hi> which is too uſual, one <hi>John Smith,</hi> a Member of <hi>Henry Ainſworth</hi>'s Church there, being excommunicated for ſome ſcandalous Offence, is reported to be one of the firſt, who baptized himſelf firſt, afterwards baptized others: and this Story brought no good report of ſuch an Adminiſtrator to <hi>Shem Acher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or two Men according to their Principle in their Judgment altogether unbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed before, did baptize one another at the firſt, and afterwards did baptize others: and ſo were many of the Baptizings in <hi>London,</hi> reported originally to be in one if not in two Inſtances, where alſo no extraordinary Call from God thereunto, that ever he yet heard of, is pretended or pleaded.</p>
               <p>Or elſe a private baptized Brother, no lawfully called Miniſter of Chriſt, nor rightly ordained Officer in a true Church, did baptize others: and ſo he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands were ſome of the choiceſt and beſt accounted Baptizings in the eſteem of many, of ſeveral of the baptized ones in <hi>London,</hi> carried on by one who always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be any Miniſter, or ordained Officer in the Church. He has been credibly informed by two yet alive in this City of <hi>London,</hi> who were Members of the firſt Church of Baptized Believers here, that their firſt Adminiſtrator was one who bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized himſelf, or elſe he and another baptized one another, and ſo gathered a Church; which was ſo oppoſed in Publick and in Private, that they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted out of their Church-State and Conſtitution, out of their Call to Office; that not being able to juſtify their Principle and Practice by the Word, they were broken and ſcattered. This, together with that which goes immediately before, he was and is diſſatisfied about: becauſe, when he doth look into both the Typical Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators in the Old Teſtament, and Antitypical ones in the New, ſtill they were in Both, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 20, 21. Gen 6, 7, 8 chapters. 1 Cor. 10. 1, 2. Iſa 40. 3, 4, 5. Mal 3. 1. Mat. 3. Mark 1. Luke 3. Joh. 1 &amp; 3 chapters. Mat. 21. 23-27. Joh. 3. 22 -26. &amp; 4 1, 2. Mat. 28. 18, 19, 20. Acts 8. 12, 26, 39.</note> Commiſſioned, Ordained Miniſters and Officers appointed thereunto, either extraordinarily and immediately by the LORD thereunto; a Call from whom they could evidence by ſomewhat extraordinary to themſelves and others, that it was a ſpecial call from <hi>Jehovah Aelohim:</hi> ſuch an Adminiſtrator was <hi>Noah</hi> in the Ark; ſuch was <hi>Moſes</hi> under the Cloud and in the Red Sea; ſuch was <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> whoſe Baptiſm was from Heaven: (Let the Queſtion here be asked, and a ſound Anſwer well returned, Who baptized <hi>John?</hi> and whence was his Baptiſm?) Such were the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and other Miniſters and Officers ordained by them, or extraordinarily and immediately ſent forth, ſpecially gifted, graced, and called by <hi>Chriſt</hi> thereunto.</p>
               <p>Or elſe ſuch one or more, whom ſuch a company of Believers who had no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called, rightly ordained Miniſter or Church-Officer amongſt them before, nor any ſuch Miniſter or Miniſters, Officer or Officers, to ordain or commiſſion ſuch, and yet do chuſe, and undertake to ordain by laying on of hands, they being all private Brethren, ſome private Brother or Brethren into the Miniſterial Office, and to ſend him or them forth to preach and to baptize: neither could this quiet his thoughts, or ſatisfy his ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Or elſe ſome ſuch one, who however pretending to be called and ſent forth by Men, yet is not gifted, graced, and qualified according to the Requirements of Chriſt in his Word, for ſuch an honourable Office, and weighty Work: here alſo he was to ſeek, and could not ſo acquieſce.</p>
               <p>Or otherwiſe, ſome ſuch who ſay they were at their firſt paſſing under this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, under an unavoidable neceſſity of doing ſomewhat this way beyond and beſides the ordinary-ſtated-Scripture-Rule and Way, which they hope the LORD did accept of, they giving to him the beſt they had according to their then-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: whereunto <hi>Shem Acher</hi> has only this to deſire of ſuch at preſent, that,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57500:10"/> they ſee well unto it, their pleaded neceſſity be ſuch an indiſpenſible real urgent unavoidable neceſſity, as the holy Scriptures do warrant; and that, they impoſe not that on him as a ſtanding Rule to ſubmit to, and to walk by, who is under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of Circumſtances, and doth derive all his Satisfaction from an higher and purer Spring. And if that Neceſſity which they plead, have led them into a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Path, which is beſides the ordinary beaten High-way of King Jeſus in his Word, they have need to bring forth ſomewhat extraordinary, which may carry along with it true-and ſelf-evidence.</p>
               <p>What other way was there then yet left in this caſe, but only this one, to his ſatisfaction; He having been before ſo quite taken off from all Men, and all Creature-Authorities in theſe matters of Religion, and having given up himſelf wholly and entirely to Chriſt as his one and only LORD and Lawgiver, and to the Word of Chriſt as the one and only Rule of Faith, Worſhip and Life, and compleat Summary of all uſeful Arts and profitable Sciences; and having had ſo many ſealing Experiences of Chriſt's more immediate and extraordinary Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Callings, Healings of Him by his holy Spirit from his Father in his Word, and having paſſed before under a being baptized with the holy Spirit, he with one more travelled from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Salisbury,</hi> where, about the middle of the Day, in the broad River of that City, which runs with living water, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his being baptized as by the Hand of Chriſt himſelf, in the Face of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and ſo paſſed under Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, and baptized another: and further alſo received Impoſition, <note n="†" place="margin">Act. 10. 41. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. They were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-choſen and ordained of God to this Office of being Witneſſes of Chriſt's Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, by his lifting up, ſtretching out, laying on of Hands: It was God's Hand who thus ſet them apart: (The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Word is afterwards u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to their Office, Acts 14 23.)</note> or ſtretching out by laying on of Hands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as from this God Man, from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tho ſitting in the higher Heaven in his glorified Humanity, <hi>Chriſt</hi> being the Author of this both Water and Spirit-Baptiſm, and ſtretching out and laying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hands.</p>
               <p>The Reader or Hearer of this <hi>Narrative,</hi> is deſired to make a little ſtand in his thoughts, and here to ponder a while upon this weighty Conſiderable. In two grand parts of this <hi>Hiſtorical Declaration,</hi> the LORD has graciouſly given unto <hi>Shem Acher</hi> ſomewhat of <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 9,—16. &amp; 12. 10, 11.</note> a Spirit of Diſcerning, whereby to diſcern Spirits for the preſent, and to foreſee ſome of thoſe Propheſied Methods which he will uſe, to ſet in order the Affairs of his Houſe towards and in the latter-day-Glory, whereby <hi>Shem</hi> is enabled to truſt Chriſt for Afterwards, or Afterneſſes, or what ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after come to paſs; The holy Spirit working and diſtributing what Gift he will to whom he will. Theſe two Parts are his more than ordinary, both Call to the Miniſterial Office and Work, and way and manner of his Perfecting of Baptiſm. Both which being more immediately derived from <note n="‖" place="margin">Eph. 1. 20,—23 &amp; 2. 19.—22. &amp; 4. 7,—16.</note> Chriſt, that Head Officer of the Church he has the advantage and opportunity of holding forth before others, this, as one of the great Truths of the <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 12.</note> preſent Age, the way and means of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi>'s bringing his People <note n="†" place="margin">Ezek. 43. 10, 11, 12. &amp; <hi>chap<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 44. throughout.</hi> Pſal. 74. 9.</note> to meaſure all Adminiſtrations according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tern and promiſed Platform will be, by raiſing up, by gifting, graceing, calling, and ſending forth ſome extraordinary Meſſenger, as from Heaven, to open, interpret, apply, and promote this revealed Myſtery, relating to the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>proaching Glory of the latter days. Do not now over-haſtily conclude, that, this is a rare Artifice, and a witty Invention, for <hi>Shem</hi> hereby to point out himſelf to be this ſpecial Prophet, by a new Name, which he aſſumes to himſelf; as if the foregoing Prophets did direct as with a Finger to him, as that <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet, or one in the Spirit of that <hi>Elijah,</hi> who was to come, and to reſtore all things, and ſo to take this glorious honour unto himſelf. For, he doth not cry up himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lf to be this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Meſſenger: tho <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> may uſe and employ whom he pleaſeth in this honourable Work, and <hi>Shem</hi> is ſomewhat prepared in Heart, by the Holy God Spirit, greatly to rejoice, and to give all the Glory to the LORD, might he live to ſee in his day and time, ſuch a Gentile-Miniſter or Miniſters, as an Angel or Angels from<note place="margin">* Pſ 12. 6. Iſa. 34. 16. Rev. 11. 19.</note> Heaven to come forth with the pure Word of God, altogether freed from all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humane Mixtures whatſoever, either the very Original it ſelf or an exact Copy word for word, and being clothed with the Spirit may preach it abroad with Power and Succeſs, tho <hi>Shem</hi> as to this more eminent Honour, were laid aſide, and might be priviledged with ſitting at the Feet of ſuch a one, to receive words as from Chriſt by ſuch an extraordinary Meſſenger. But, this is that which he has further to ſay in this matter; that, he takes it for a ſpecial Favour freely beſtowed upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57500:11"/> him, that, the LORD has revealed this inner Secret to him, and has ſo far made uſe of him as to aſſert and revive the Doctrine, and ſomewhat to prepare the way for the coming of <hi>Jehovah</hi> Chriſt in the conſpicuous Appearance of his Perſonal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: before which time he will by Voice direct, and call and ſend ſome peculiar Officer or Officers of his, as <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 6, 7, 8, 9. &amp; 42 4, 16, 21. 1 Pet. 1. 23, 24, 25.</note> a publick Cryer, with this Royal Proclamation: That, this Chriſt as King of Kings, and LORD of Lords, is about to come to crown his Kingly Law, his written Word and revealed Will therein, as the one, and the only living abiding Rule, for all Churches and States to walk and to meaſure All by: let the Scriptures in the Margin be noted well. Theſe Cryers and Proclaimers are publick Officers to give open notice of ſome State or Church-Affair, whereof the ſupream King, Prieſt, and Prophet, the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, thinks good to advertize his Subjects, as by ſound of trumpeting Voice; that, all and every one who are concerned may have the certain knowledg and timely warning thereof; It muſt be with ſuch a vehement ſound as is heard at a far diſtance, that, no one may pretend or plead Ignorance, when within hearing; with the Voice of one crying, calling by Name thoſe he meets, and by expreſs Word, gathering a Convocation and Aſſembly, reading ſome part of the Book and Law and Will of God, preaching ſome Evangelical Word unto them, who give the hearing: For, this Voice, in the 6, 7, &amp; 8, <hi>ver.</hi> of the <hi>40th chap.</hi> of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> is diſtinct from the foregoing Voice, in the 3, &amp; 4, <hi>ver.</hi> which was more fulfilled in and by the Miniſtry of <note n="†" place="margin">Mal. 3. 1. Mat. 3. 3. Mar. 1. 2, 3. Luk. 3. 2,—5. Iſa. 52. 7, 8. &amp; 60. 5, 10, 16 &amp; 61. 4, 5, 6, 9. &amp; 62 6. &amp; 66. 12, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt. <hi>John</hi> delivered his Meſſage faithfully both as to his Miniſterial and Baptiſmal Office, at the enterance of the New-Teſtament-Adminiſtration of Grace, when Chriſt was coming ſhortly after in his ſtate of Humiliation. But, ſome other or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, will be called and ſent forth about this latter, and toward the latter-day-Glory, a little before Chriſt's coming in the Clouds in his ſtate of Exaltation, as the 9, 10, &amp; 11, <hi>ver.</hi> of the formentioned <hi>Chapter</hi> will evidence, to a diſcerning conſiderate Reader, when the <hi>Sioners</hi> ſhall be Evangalized and gathered into Church-Flocks, unto a purer way than ever yet. When the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be in a preparedneſs for this great turn, and thereby made ready for the LORD, at that time, <note n="*" place="margin">Song. 8. 8, 9, 10.</note> as at the beginning of the New-Teſtament-Diſpenſation of Grace, ſome Miniſters from among the <hi>Jews</hi> were employed in converting and baptizing of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> ſo now in theſe later days, ſome of the <hi>Gentile</hi>-Miniſters, may have the honour to be Inſtruments under Chriſt, of converting and baptizing of the <hi>Jews:</hi> And where can that People find a meet Adminiſtrator, if the LORD do not more immediately ſend them ſome Prophet, who can prove his Miſſion and Commiſſion to be from on High? <hi>They ſtill requiring a Sign,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 22. For, as for thoſe few of their Brethren in this day, who by outward Profeſſion and Confeſſion do own Chriſt to be the true <hi>Meſſiah</hi> already come in the Fleſh, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> never yet met with any of them, (he has conferred with about five or ſix of ſuch) who come forth with any thing extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, viſible mark and gift upon them, as to a being clothed with the Spirit. And that Baptiſm which they have received, at leaſt ſome of them, if not all, has been from corrupt hands in a corrupt way: And <hi>Shem</hi> doth bear good will towards that People, praying for <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s Peace, and for <hi>Sion</hi>'s Purity, ſeeking the good of her Sons and Daughters, and having experienced the Truth and Goodneſs of that Promiſe more ways than one, that, ſuch ſhall proſper who love her. Beſides, there may be divers of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who a little before God's thus favouring of <hi>Sion,</hi> may be brought more throughly into a perfecting of their Baptiſm, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Seekers, non-Church-Men, and ſeveral others, upon ſome of whoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits this doth lye with preſſing weight; whither ſhall we go to meet with a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully-called-Miniſtry, and a lawfully-conſtituted Church? where is there a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranted, heavenly atteſted-Adminiſtrator? <hi>Shem</hi> in this doth ſpeak out ſome of the Thoughts of ſuch diſſatisfied ones, and he is ſo far ready with an anſwer, which he can give to thoſe, who ask him a word concerning his Miniſtry and Baptiſm; Whence is thy Miniſtry and Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſm, and from whom thy Miniſtry and Baptiſm? as to the perfecting of both, it is from Heaven not from Earth, from Chriſt more immediately and not ſo from Men. Here, in the way, let it be remembred, that, the reviving of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, doth make way for the later-day-Glory-Converſions, and Ingatherings of the Outcaſts of <hi>Iſrael, Iſa.</hi> 56. 1,—8. And that, the Prophecies and Promiſes of building the old waſte places, and of raiſing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57500:11"/> up the Foundations of many Generations, and of being called the Repairer of the Breach, the Reſtorer and Paths to Sabbatize is made over to ſuch Revivers of the Seventh-day-Sabbath. This great uſeful Truth is therefore not only received in the Principle, but alſo cloſed with in the Practice, by <hi>Shem Acher:</hi> wherein he doth ſweetly acquieſce to his own ſatisfaction, whilſt others do diſpute, preach and print, to defend and juſtify their various Calls to both, by Arguments moſtly drawn from Men, tho running down to them in a very corrupt Channel; and if his LORD ſhould ſay to his Servant <hi>Shem,</hi> as once to <note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 12. v. 13 Iſa. 58. 12, 13, 14. &amp; 66. 21, 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel,</hi> And thou, <hi>Shem Acher, Go to the end, and thou ſhalt reſt, and ſhalt ſtand in thy lot to the end of thoſe days;</hi> let it ſuffice thee, that <hi>Jehovah</hi> thy <hi>Aelohim</hi> hath revealed this in thee, and done this for thee: but the larger pourings out of the Spirit, and more ſignal ownings are reſerved for ſome others: yet even this is a ſpecial honour, and the Glory be to him.</p>
               <p>It is well worthy of an obſervable Remark in Scripture, that, beſides the ſtated Miniſtry, the LORD has ſent forth ſpecial Prophets and Apoſtles, upon urgent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions: Some of theſe were of another Education and Profeſſion, ſuch as <note n="†" place="margin">Amos 1. 1. &amp; 7. 14, 15. Acts 7 42. &amp; 15. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Amos,</hi> who had been no Prophet, nor Prophets Son, but an Herdſman, and a Gatherer of Fruit. Thus alſo <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 4. 18, 19, 20.</note> the Apoſtles in Chriſt's time were ſome of them, poor plain Fiſhermen. <hi>Jehovah</hi> communicated Himſelf and his Will unto ſuch in extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Revelations, and confirmed their Office by miraculous atteſts from Heaven. In other Inſtances, he has dignified ſome with ſuch ſpecial ſingular Employs, in a Miniſtry not common, <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 7. 22. Dan. 1. 4, 17. Acts 22. 3 2 Cor. 12. 11. 1 Cor. 14. 18.</note> who were skilled in great variety of Arts and Sciences, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in Scripture-Knowledges, in which latter he bleſſed their Studies and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and encouraged their Diligence and Induſtry. So it was with <hi>Moſes, Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, Paul,</hi> and others. <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 28 8. Luke 1. 70. &amp; 11. 50. Act. 3. 21.</note> Prophets there have been in all the Ages of the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſtanding Miniſtry. Before <hi>Moſes</hi> there were, <hi>Adam, Enoch, Noah, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, Jacob, Joſeph.</hi> Afterwards, there were, <hi>Moſes, Joſhuah, Samuel, David, Solomon, Nathan, Gad, Elijah, Eliſha, Michajah, Eſaias, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Daniel, Hoſea, Joel, Amos, Obadiah, Jonah, Micah, Nahum, Habakkuk, Zepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah, Haggai, Zechariah, Malachi, Zecharias</hi> the Father of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. In the New Teſtament, <hi>Simeon, Agabus;</hi> the good Apoſtles, by Name particularly, <hi>Peter, John, Paul,</hi> and others. <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 28, 29. Eph. 4. 11, 12, 13. Act. 13. 1. 1 Cor. 14. <hi>chap.</hi>
                  </note> Apoſtles, and Prophets, are expreſly mentioned as eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Officers, ſet and appointed by Chriſt in his Church. This was not confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned only to <hi>Judea;</hi> for, in other parts of the inhabited Earth, there was <hi>Job, Eliphaz,</hi> and others in the Eaſt, who were eminent Leaders of Congregated Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, and there was a <hi>Balaam</hi> of <hi>Syria, Meſopotamia,</hi> who had a Prophetick Gift.</p>
               <p>To diſtinguiſh of Prophets, and of the ſeveral kinds of them, and of the diſtinct parts of their Office, is not my preſent work: let it ſuffice at this time to ſhew, that, the LORD has not been wanting to his Church and People, when he has been ſought unto aright; as to his gifting, gracing, calling and ſending extraordinary Officers (with a larger Commiſſion than only to a ſmall gathered handful of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt) when the ordinary ones have been corrupted or negligent, ignorant or unfaithful, or upon ſome other ſpecial Occaſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shem</hi> in his own caſe, tho altogether unworthy of the leaſt and loweſt place of Service miniſterial in Chriſt's Houſe, yet for about theſe twenty years laſt paſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Chriſt's Servant, to gather, feed, and rule a particular Church, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, and to this day is ſo, he has declared againſt his being ſtaked or teddered down to any one Place or People, he being Chriſt's Servant, at his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters diſpoſe, to do what publick work his LORD ſhall call him unto, whereſoever, to whomſoever it be, having never as yet, either ſingly by himſelf, or jointly with others, laid on his Hands upon any one, as to an ordaining of him to the Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Office.</p>
               <p>This part of <hi>Shem</hi>'s Narrative ſhould put ſome diſſenting Brethren upon more ſerious conſidering, whether, they have not been very ſhort of their Duty, who have cryed down, and run down all gathered Churches and Church-Miniſters, (becauſe of ſome Antichriſtian and Unſcriptural Principles and Practices corruptly crept in) ſome for five, others for ten, ſome others for twenty, otherſome for thirty years together, not ſeeing, or not believing, or not acknowledging, or not promoting, any extraordinary Miniſtry over gathered Curch, or Churches, ſet up
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57500:12"/> by Chriſt in the room thereof? And, O! who will give, that, this ſeaſonable Word might fall and abide with kindly in working Efficacy, in the demonſtration of the Spirit, and with power upon prepared Hearts, and unprejudiced Minds; both as to non-Church ones, and alſo as to the preſent Claimers of Miniſtry, by Office, whether National, Claſſical, Congregational, pleading for a right in their Tenure, whether by Succeſſion, Authority from the People, or what elſe? That, one and another may yet be think themſelves of a more Scriptural way, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, ſetling, ſatisfying, healing and uniting of Chriſtians. As Scripture-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory doth clear it up, that ſo it hath been, ſo Scripture-Prophecy and Scripture-Promiſe will fulfil and accompliſh it, that, ſo it ſhall be in this latter-day-Glory, even a Prophetick, Apoſtolick, Evangelick, and otherways extraordinary Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as well as a Paſtoral, Teaching, ordinary Miniſtry, revived and advanced, continued and bleſſed, ſuch ſpecial Adminiſtrators in Chriſt's Houſe, by whom reſort ſhall be to the Mouth of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to ask Counſel at an Oracle of <hi>Aelohim;</hi> who has in all Ages of his Church, both before and ſince the Apoſtle's days, ſent ſome ſpecial Meſſenger or Meſſengers to witneſs for Himſelf, and for the Truths of Chriſtian Religion, againſt the Corruptions of the Times and Age wherein they lived, tho the number of ſuch under many Providences has been but ſmall, and the true Miniſtry and Churches have not ſo ſhined forth with viſible Pomp, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Glory.</p>
               <p>There may, if <hi>Jehovah</hi> our <hi>Aelohim</hi> and <hi>Adonai,</hi> do bring it forth by and in the Hand of his Providence, ſhortly come abroad a Scripture-Directory, concerning an Houſe for the Sons of the Prophets, for the training up of ſuch, whoſe Hearts the LORD ſhall make willing to ſtudy uſeful Arts and Sciences in the Book of Books, the Holy Scriptures of Truth, Inſpired Gifts, and Acquired Gifts, where <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 14, 15, 16, 17. 1 Sam. 10. 5,—13. 2 Kings 2. 3, 5, 7, 16. &amp; 4. 38.</note> both are ſanctified, how uſeful are they when employed for the Edification of the Church and People of Chriſt? And, who of us can tell, but that the open declaring for both theſe by ſome <hi>Gentile</hi>-Chriſtians, and Believers, and Miniſters, who expreſs their Faith in Prophetick Scriptures, that <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 32. 15. &amp; 44. 3, 4. Ezek. 39, 29. Joel 2. 28,—32. Ezek. 47. 1,—12. 1 Cor. 12, 13, 14. <hi>ch.</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 17. 18.</note> there are near at hand ſome further more immediate Inſpirings from the Holy Spirit with extraordinary Chariſms, or edifying Gifts, and thoſe of working of Miracles, and Gifts of Healings, and of Tongues particularly; (For, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 22, 24.</note> the <hi>Jews</hi> do to this day require a Sign) and who withal do in the uſe of ordinary means wait upon the Holy Spirit for his inner Teachings, and for his Bleſſings of their unwearied Endeavours, and diligent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, of their ſerious cryings after Scripture-Knowledg in the Original Language, and giving their Voice for Underſtanding, ſeeking her as Silver, and ſearching for her as hid Treaſures: For, (the <hi>Greeks</hi> do ſtill ſeek after Wiſdom, I ſay, who knows, but that) both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> may fall in love with this Art of Arts, and Science of Sciences, if <hi>Jehovah</hi> will in either, or in both theſe ways give Wiſdom; out of whoſe Mouth Knowledg and Underſtanding: when Wiſdom ſhall thus enter into Hearts, Oh! how pleaſant will Knowledg be to the Soul? <note n="†" place="margin">Mar. 16. 15. Mat. 28. 18, 19, 20. Gal. 2. 7, 8. Iſa. 40. 9. &amp; 52. 7, 8.</note> As the LORD here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore honoured ſome of the Chriſtianized <hi>Jews</hi> to be under him his Apoſtles, for the converting of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> ſo, in theſe later Days, he may honour, ſome of the Chriſtianized <hi>Gentiles</hi> to be under him his Apoſtles, for the converting of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Zech. 2. 5. Iſa. 46. 13.</note> then ſhall the LORD and his new created Ones, be the mutual Glory of each other. Oh! how glorious a Day will that Day of ſuch Glory be!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 9. 15,—20. &amp; 26. 16,—20. 1 Cor. 15. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> being thus put by Chriſt into the Miniſterial Office, ſets about the work wherein he laboured more abundantly than all the Apoſtles: his Travels up and down with the Goſpel, as one Hiſtorian has computed them, were ten thouſand two hundred and ſeventy Miles, from his firſt beginning, until his being Priſoner in <hi>Rome;</hi> and altho he might have required maintenance, <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 9, 10, 11, 12. &amp; 12. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. 1 Cor. 9. <hi>thorow.</hi>
                  </note> yet for the Goſpel's ſake he did forbear the demanding of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 21. <hi>and ſo to the end.</hi> &amp; 4. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Gal. 6. 17. Rom. 3, 8.</note> His Sufferings were many and great; his being reproached was his ſore Tryal: particularly that, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 5.</note> for his leading about of a Siſter a Wife.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 28.</note> He had care of all the Churches.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57500:12"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 9. 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 38. &amp; 11. 26. &amp; 14. 22, 28. &amp; 18. 23, 27. &amp; 19. 1, 9. &amp; 20. 1. 7. &amp; 21. 4, 16. 1 Cor. 16. 10, 11, 12. 2 Cor. 8. 16, 17, 18. Deut. 18. 6, 7, 8. 1 Cor. 3. 21, 22.</note> Where he made or found thorow Diſciples of Chriſt in any City, Town, or elſewhere, he had and held actual Communion with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>Since Chriſt's more thorow Calling of <hi>Shem Acher</hi> to this Office and Work of the Miniſtry, the LORD has given him a willing and ready mind and heart, glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſpend and be ſpent in his Service, and for Souls; and although his Travels have not been comparable for Miles and for Countries with <hi>Paul</hi>'s, yet he has had a Deſire that way, if Chriſt had called, and enabled him thereunto; and he had this Honour put upon him, to be one of the firſt who ſet up open Separate Meetings in two or three Counties. And for his Diligence in Preaching, it is well known to many, of which he gave good Teſtimony through Grace (to the God of which Grace he aſcribes all the Honour) eſpecially for five years in a great Town in <hi>Dorcetſhire,</hi> and afterwards, whilſt above nine years the LORD's Priſoner, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the latter end of which part of his Confinement in <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> he did preach ſixteen times a week for ſome weeks, beſides other occaſional work; and ſince his coming near, or into the City of <hi>London,</hi> he has not been idle.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>filthy Lucre,</hi> he has not greedily ſought it. Whilſt he received Tithe-Maintenance in a private Pariſh, which was near one Hundred pounds by the year, it was ſpent amongſt them in Hoſpitality, in providing for the Poor, in buying of Bibles and ſuch like, in ſetting the Poor on work; for he ſuffered no Beggar knowingly of all the Pariſhioners: and towards parting with them, he laid out about three hundred pounds in building a new Houſe, which he left to ſuch as ſhould after ſucceed him to labour in the Word and Doctrine. This Eſtate he freely left, to anſwer a Call unto a Neighbour Town, where was much Work, and little Wages; For, the ſmall Tithes belonging to the Vicarage were ſo inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that when one whole years Profits were given to the King upon the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence-Act, the Man who was to gather the Profits for the King, had at the years end laid out about five ſhillings more for decimation and in collecting than he had received: which he doth not mention to reflect it upon the Inhabitants of that Town, ſome whereof were not backward in contributing; but all that, and fourſcore pounds Annuity of his own, ſetled upon him by his Father, was ſpent upon the place (except what was laid out in Books, and ſuch like.) He alſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtored Thirty pounds, out of which himſelf took not one ſhilling, which was procured by ſome of the Town, and paid to an Aſſiſtant, as an Augmentation, which ran in <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s other-Name. If any take himſelf to have been wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or defrauded by him, let ſuch prove the Charge, and he will make Reſtitution; <hi>Numb. 16. 15. 1 Sam. 12. 3, 4, 5. Luke 19. 8. 2 Cor.</hi> 7. 2. For ſeventeen years or thereabouts, altho he hath refuſed many pounds, yet he doth remember but one piece of Tithe that he received of any, which was brought to him by a Fellow-Priſoner, conſcientiouſly, as ſhe declared, which was a very little Pot of Honey, the Tenth-part of ſome Hive-Honey which ſhe had in a little Garden of hers in the Country; which, to ſatisfie her, he did receive from her hands, but he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave it back to her again, and a ſhilling beſides. This he doth mention, to wipe off that Slander of Self-ſeeking; who during his Ten-days Tribulation, lived up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Annuity, whilſt a Priſoner: and ſince his coming to <hi>London,</hi> he has done the ſame. Tho his Judgment be, that Decimation is the Peoples Duty, about which he hath drawn up ſeveral Arguments in another Paper, reſerved for ſuch a ſeaſon, when ſuch Doctrine is like to have a readier reception.</p>
               <p>What his Sufferings have been, are well known to ſome <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2. 10.</note>, in nine full years cloſe and hard Impriſonment, and the beginning of a tenth; beſides thoſe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Reproaches, Slanders, and other Oppoſings which have aſſaulted him for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe laſt ſeventeen years more eſpecially, both from declared Enemies, and pretended Friends: But, bleſſed be <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who has enabled him in any good meaſure <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 3.—10.</note> to endeavour to give no juſt offence, or occaſion of falling in any thing, that the Miniſtry might not be blamed; but in all things has endeavoured to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf as a Miniſter of God, <hi>in much Patience, in Afflictions, in Diſtreſſes, in Impriſonments, in Labours, in</hi> ſome <hi>Watchings, and Faſtings; by Pureneſs, by Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57500:13"/> by Long-ſuffering, by Kindneſs, by the Holy Spirit, by Love unfeigned, by the Word of Truth, by the Power of God, by the Armour of Righteouſneſs on the right hand and on the left, by Honour and Diſhonour, by evil report and good report: As a Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and yet true; as unknown</hi> to many, <hi>and yet</hi> well acknowledged by ſome; <hi>as dying, and yet behold he lives; as chaſtened, and not killed; as ſorrowful, yet always rejoicing.</hi> He forbears to enlarge much more upon this, as not knowing how that will be received which is already mentioned: However, he doth <note n="†" place="margin">Col. 1. 24.</note> rejoice in his Sufferings for the LORD's People, and by way of Correſpondence and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to Chriſt, is filling up that which is behind of the Afflictions of Chriſt in his Fleſh, for his Bodies ſake, which is the Church. <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 9. <hi>and in many other p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aces of the Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> Mat 3. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. &amp; 4. 1,—17.</note> As it was with <hi>Paul,</hi> and as it was with Chriſt, ſo alſo with <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> a flood of Temptations and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions brake in upon him when he thus paſſed under perfecting the Ordinance of Baptiſm, and into a more thorow diſcharge of his Miniſterial Function.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Paul</hi> was, ſo alſo has <hi>Shem Acher</hi> been much ſlanderouſly miſreported con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Authority and Power of leading about of a Siſter, a Wife, in his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels. Hiſtorians do differ in their Judgment about <hi>Paul,</hi> whether he were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally married or not: <hi>Euſebius Pamphilus</hi> nameth <hi>Clemens</hi> and <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and ſome others there are w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o hold that he was married. That which doth perſwade <hi>Shem Acher</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> was married, beſides ſomewhat elſe which he could produce that way, is <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 7.</note> that expreſſion of <hi>Paul, I would that all Men were even as I my ſelf,</hi> which being interpreted of abſtaining from Marriage altogether, were a very ſinful wiſh in him: For, if ſimply and abſolutely taken, if ſuch a Will and Deſire had obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all the Race of Mankind, and the whole Church of Chriſt, in two Generations had been utterly extinct. However the Caſe was with <hi>Paul, Shem Acher</hi> has been very unkindly and injuriouſly dealt withal about his Marriage with <hi>Gnezri-jah.</hi> When he (with ſome other Miniſters) had the Honour to be ſo many years the LORD's Priſoner at <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> it came upon and into the Heart of <hi>Gnezri-jah,</hi> from the time of his (and their) firſt Confinement, to be as a common Stewardeſs and Nurſe, to make and bring in Proviſion of Food, and of other outward Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for them, her Spirit and Soul being much drawn forth in Compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the LORD's ſuffering Servants, in fellow-feeling of their Hardſhips, and with great longings after the daily enjoyment of Communion with Father, Son, and holy Spirit, by the LORD's Bleſſing upon his and others Miniſterial Labours: at which time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho ſhe then had an aged Mother to maintain, ſhe did pinch and ſtraiten her ſelf, in diet and other-ways, to ſerve and be helpful unto thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; which was afterwards underſtood by <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> and conſidered by him. After ſome time the other Miniſters having obtained their Liberty, <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment was continued for ſeveral years; all which time this <hi>Gnezri-jah</hi> was a ſuccourer of him, and did continue friendly &amp; faithful to him in all his Temptations, and was very uſeful, not only to him, but alſo to many other of the Priſoners in divers caſes. When he was ſet free, his Heart was engaged to preach the Goſpel abroad; and having need of help, <hi>Gnezri-jah</hi> ſometimes travelled with him; This being envied and maligned by ſome, to prevent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or remove any occaſion of Scandal or offence, he declared unto ſome of the Church, that he was willing to take <hi>Gnezri-jah</hi> to him for a Wife, according to the Word, ſhe being every way the fitteſt for him, ſhe being a Siſter in the ſame way of Church-Fellowſhip, and a Virgin modeſt and chaſt, many ways look'd upon as excelling almoſt all of her Sex in the whole Town of <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> for Humility, Patience, Mortifiedneſs, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, Faithfulneſs, Zeal, and ſuch Commendableneſſes as theſe, in the Judgment of all ſpiritual Diſcerners, who had any intimate acquaintance with her; and ſhe having undergone ſo many Hardſhips and Difficulties for him, and after ſo many years experience of her fittedneſs for ſuch a Yoke-fellowſhip, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> married her. When this was made known, the Tempter beſtirred himſelf, and ſet ſome upon opening of their mouths both againſt him and her, that he had married one who had been a kind of Servant to him, one much beneath him for Birth, a poor Maid without a Portion: which was ſo odiouſly and unjuſtly aggravated and ſpread abroad by ſome, who ſhould have been more friendly, (both he and ſhe before then, and ſince, having been friendly unto them) that his Miniſtry was in a great meaſure rendred much uſeleſs and ſucceſsleſs in thoſe Parts; which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57500:13"/> of Marriage a little after compleated, together with the Advice of ſeveral of the Friends in Fellowſhip with him, to publiſh a Treatiſe in the Defence of the Cauſe of the <hi>Seventh-Day-Sabbath,</hi> was ſomewhat of the occaſion both of his coming to, and continuing near and in the City of <hi>London.</hi> Thus muſt any thing a little colourable, ſerve for a Charge againſt <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> who has met with a paſſage in <hi>Clarks</hi> Lives, where he makes mention of a Commendable Act of one Miniſter of Chriſt, who having bin helped by a mean Handmaid, a Virgin, during his ſore Impriſonment for the Goſpel's ſake, when he was ſet at Liberty, thought he could no other way ſo requite her, as by marrying of her. This is recorded to the praiſe of that Miniſter; but, if <hi>Shem Acher</hi> do the ſame, it muſt be look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by many as a Scandal and Crime in him. As for a Portion, he prizeth Grace at a very low rate, who doth not really in a caſe of competition, eſteem and prefer it above and beyond many Bags of Earthly Treaſure: And altho <hi>Shem Acher</hi> might poſſibly have had ſeveral Thouſands with another Woman, where there was not ſuch a ſuitableneſs in other reſpects; yet it was a ſweet ſenſible Evidence upon his Heart in his Conſcience about that time, that being cloſely held to that <note n="†" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 72, 127.</note> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-term, he readily complied with it, and conformed to it, in the ſtrength and ſupplies of the holy Spirit. <hi>The Law of thy mouth, O Jehovah, is better unto me than Thouſands of Gold and of Silver. Therefore I love thy Commandments above Gold, yea, above fine Gold. Shem Acher</hi> having an Annuity of Fourſcore pounds by the year, ſetled upon him during his Life, This provided Food convenient, and other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Neceſſaries for him, and out of the reſt he was ready to diſtribute out of the Decimation, and otherwiſe, to the Neceſſities of others proportionably as far as it would go; ſo that now, after twenty years or more enjoyment of that Annuity, he has not laid up one ſhilling out of that Means, if he die before <hi>Gnezri-jah,</hi> what he has to leave her is moſtly his Study of Books, and ſome Houſhold-ſtuff. They have not wanted Conveniencies ſince they came together, neither ſhall either of them want when they are parted aſunder by Death; for they have Bonds by gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Covenant under the Hand and Seal of the faithful God, to be cared and provided for: But, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> not having an Eſtate to ſettle any Jointure upon a Wife, if ſhe ſurvived, he never had any conſiderable Proffer made him, neither did ever meet with any pure Virgin ſo every way a meet help for him. The common corrupt practice amongſt many of the Gentry, being to ſettle almoſt all their Eſtate upon their Eldeſt Son (which has brought a Curſe upon, and has bin the Ruin of many Antient and Honorable, wealthy Families, the LORD in the way his Providence frowning upon ſuch an unſcriptural diſtribution, He allowing a <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 21. 17.</note> double portion of their Father's Goods to the Firſt-born) whereas younger-Brothers are often put off with ſome ſmall Allowance to keep them alive. This <hi>Shem Acher</hi> doth mention, not at all out of diſcontent at his Allotment; for, he doth write as he hath long experienced, that his Annuity is the wiſeſt and beſt Portion and Proviſion for him, it bringing in unto him a Competency, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging him from Worldly Cares, and Earthly Incumbrances; all his labour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this being once a Quarter to receive Twenty pounds, and to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance: Only he brings in here this Teſtimony againſt the fore-mentioned common corrupt Practice. As for <hi>Gnezri-jah</hi>'s Family and Relations, An ancient Juſtice of Peace did declare, that her Grandfather was one of the Firſt who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for a Reformation againſt the Superſtitions and other Corruptions of the Times, to the endangering of his Liberty and Life; and that he, and a Kinſman of his, did lend one hundred pounds to Mr. <hi>White</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> for his encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who was one of the firſt and foremoſt and forwardeſt of all the <hi>Puritane</hi>-Miniſters in the Weſt, publickly by Preaching, and otherwiſe, to promote a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. He dipped all his Children. This Mr. <hi>Slado</hi> her Grandfather had a conſiderable Eſtate in <hi>England,</hi> which he ſold, and purchaſed ſomewhat in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> he had a numerous Progeny, and they moſt of them have proſpered well in this World, and divers of them fear the LORD: ſeveral of them are ſtill living. Whilſt he lived in the City of <hi>Limerick</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Lecturers were entertained at his Houſe; Two of his Daughters were there married to Miniſters. One Mr. <hi>Town,</hi> who married <hi>Gnezri-jah</hi>'s Mother, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> has heard was a Doctor of Divinity, having Preferments in <hi>Ireland</hi> worth Two hundred pounds by the year,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57500:14"/> he kept ſeven or eight Servants and well bred up a fruitful Family. Her Father ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Light of that day was zealous againſt Popery, often expoſing his Life to danger in defence of the Proteſtant Religion; once the bloody Papiſts at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to bury him alive: but, the LORD delivered him. In the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about forty years ago, this Doctor with all his Family were perſecuted; he left his Eſtate for the Cauſe of Chriſt; and after many wonderful deliverances in <hi>Ireland</hi> and at Sea, during that Rebellion, ſeveral of his Family came for <hi>England,</hi> where the LORD took care of them; but now they are ſcattered into ſeveral Countries. Yet notwithſtanding this juſt Defence made as to Men, ſome do ſtill go on with their defamings both of <hi>Shem Acher</hi> and of <hi>Gnezri-jah</hi> about this Matter, who leave their Cauſe with the righteous Judg, who knows, how they both for ſeveral years have much endeavoured to ſweeten the Lives of others, and to promote Peace and Purity in the Churches: tho ill requited by many, whoſe unkindneſs have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted much towards the breaking down of her Conſtitution, and the ſore diſtreſſing of her Spirit; ſo that, it is a wonderful Power and Preſervation, that, both her Husband and ſhe are yet alive.</p>
               <p>What careful Thoughts <hi>Shem Acher</hi> has had for the Churches of the Holy Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to his Capacity, Opportunity and Ability, is known to the ſearcher of Hearts, and there are ſome Friends who have been acquainted therewith; tho hitherto he has been but little encouraged, and cannot effect much: but, ſome Teſtimony thereof he has brought in this way, by a Treatiſe of his publiſhed in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty ſeven, called, <hi>All in One, &amp;c.</hi> by the Viſits which he has given to Sabbath-Churches, and that Epiſtle of Love which he this Year ſent to them for a Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting in <hi>London,</hi> by Meſſengers, for the promoting of ſuch good Work and great Ends, as were well worthy for the greateſt Princes, and ableſt Miniſters, to countenance and proſecute: had it been entertained and improved according to its juſt due value; Which Epiſtle of Love was as followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>Shem Acher</hi> a Servant and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Friends in Church-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him, in <hi>London,</hi> To all the Churches of Seventh-day-Sabbath-Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, who keep the Commandments of God, and the Faith and the Teſtimony of Jeſus; Sendeth a Chriſtian Salutation of Brotherly Love: Mercy, Grace, Love, Peace, and Bleſſing be multiplyed to you from God our Father, and the LORD Jeſus Chriſt.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE give thanks to God and the Father of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt, who has made known to you and to us his Holy Sabbath, and hath ſo far favoured and honoured us, as to uſe and own our open Confeſſing, and obedient Witneſſing of this, and of any other Truth and Duty of the preſent Age, whereunto he hath called us forth in his Wiſdom and Strength, who are but Fooliſh and Weak in our ſelves; and we earneſtly deſire you to help together, by Prayer with us, that, both you and we may walk worthy of God, who hath thus called us unto his Kingdom and Glory; and who has made King Jeſus to be Preciouſneſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to us, and his Kingly Law to be Honourable and Glorious in our Eſteem: Both the Old and New Teſtament towards the cloſe of each, putting us upon a more particular and eſpecial remembrance of Him and of his Law; and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thoſe to be the Bleſſed Ones, who doing his Commandments, that, they may have right to the Tree of Life, and may enter in through the Gates into the City.</p>
                     <p>There being divers exceeding great and precious Prophecies and Promiſes, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting more peculiarly unto the Revivers and Obſervers of the weekly Seventh-day-Sabbath, which ſhall go a little before the Coming and Appearing of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt in Glory, when he will gather in the out-caſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and do his other latter day-Glory-works; For, there ſhall be thoſe of ſuch Chriſtian belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Sabbath-keepers, who ſhall build all the old waſte places, who ſhall raiſe up the Foundations from Generation to Generation, and who ſhall be called Menders of Breaches, Reſtorers of Paths to Sabbatize in, and, the time drawing on, Chriſt's Salvation being at hand to come, and his Righteouſneſs to be revealed, ſo that,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57500:14"/> we ſhould look up, and lift up our Heads, becauſe ſuch our Redemption draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth near.</p>
                     <p>We therefore propound this unto your ſerious Conſideration, dear Brethren, beloved in our LORD, that, by two or more Meſſengers from every ſuch Church in <hi>England,</hi> or by Letters and Meſſages from any of ſuch Churches, or of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Brethren in <hi>Holland, New-England,</hi> or elſewhere, we may meet, if our LORD will, once, or oftner upon weighty and urgent occaſions and neceſſities, every Year at <hi>London,</hi> or elſewhere, at ſuch times as ſhall be agreed on, to keep days of Faſting and of Thankſgiving together, by the Prayers of Faith, through the Mediation and Interceſſion of the great Apoſtle, and High Prieſt of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Jeſus Chriſt, to prevail with the Father for larger pourings out of his Spirit upon our ſelves, and upon others, for his ſpecial preſence of Grace with us, aſſiſting and bleſſing of us in all Church-Adminiſtrations, and at ſuch a general Meeting by Meſſengers; ſo, as that thereby there may be begotten a better Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and a more unanimous Accord among our ſelves, a more ſucceſsful carrying on of Truth, Love, Peace, and Holineſs in our Churches, a more exact bringing of all the Ordinances of Chriſt's New Spiritual Houſe to the Laws and Orders of the Prophetical Pattern according to Scripture-Inſtitution, and that, from cool conſiderate Conferences there may be given forth right ſtatings of any other Queſtions that may come before us, about which to give our advice mutually to one another, by the Rules of the Word of God, judging righteous Judgment according unto that, without any lording it one over another, but in all lowlineſs of Mind, in Humility and Meekneſs, being readily and thankfully made willing to receive further Scripture-Light from any, whom our LORD ſhall uſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to hold it forth before us; and that, then and there we may conſult which way by a common ſtock to promote any good work, for the maintenance of any Church-Officers, for the training up of hopeful young, or more aged Men (ſound and ſtedfaſt in the Faith) in the Knowledg of the Original Tongue, and of other Scripture-Learning, and for the procuring of a more exact literal Tranſlation of the Old-and New-Teſtament into our Mother-Tongue, and for the more religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous educating of Children, in Families and in Schools, and for the relieving of the Poor, and for ſuch other good Works; and to enquire, what may be further a Duty upon us, towards the two, and the ten Tribes of <hi>Judah,</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to help forward their Converſion, as alſo what the Spirit has to ſay more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eſpecially to our Churches, and to other Churches, in this great Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial-day, and ſuch like publick-ſpirited Inquiries: and all this for the promoting of the Honour of our LORD, and of his Word, Works, and Cauſe, the Purity and Peace of Churches and Salvation of Souls.</p>
                     <p>Thus, through Grace, and Mercy, obtained from our LORD, we diſcover and declare our readineſs to joyn in with you, in what is the work of our Day and Generation, and ſo commend you to God, and to the Word of his Grace, which is able to build you and us up, and to give us an Inheritance among all them who are Sanctified.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Shem Acher.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Now that <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s Ends towards the latter-day-Glory might be promoted, and that <hi>Shem</hi> might proſecute ſo good a deſign in the uſe of all thoſe lawful means, which his Line could reach into, in his place, for the finiſhing of this part of his Teſtimony for Chriſt, for the Word of Chriſt, for the Law of his ten Words and the annexed Judicials, and for the Seventh-day-Sabbath more eſpecially; whilſt others were following of the King with Petition upon Petition, ſubſcribed with multitudes of Hands, from Cities, Towns, and Counties: By <hi>Shem</hi>'s dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, this following Addreſs was put into the Hands of the King.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57500:15"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe Land doth tremble, it is broken, it ſhaketh: the right Way, and proper Method to heal its Breaches is plain and evident.</p>
                     <p>You have ſeen the Hand of the LORD ſtretched out againſt the Popiſh Plotters, in a continued Diſcovery for many Months of their bloody Deſign.</p>
                     <p>If the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, who is the King of Kings, would graciouſly give you a Heart for it, and then put it into your Heart, openly at the next Seſſion of Parliament, to declare, that, It is your full Purpoſe, and firm Reſolution, in the Strength and Supplies of the Almighty God, to ſet up the Laws of Chriſt in the Scriptures of Truth, as the one, and the only Rule of your Government, for which you have their own Authority in expreſs Words, The Law of God is the Law of the Land.</p>
                     <p>Then will your Name be tranſmitted to Poſterity in the <hi>Engliſh Chronicle,</hi> with a Crown Royal upon it, Thoſe who honour Chriſt, he will honour.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>This from a mean Handmaid, Elizabeth Hooker.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Sabbath of my (Mighty) God make thou it Precious, O my God of Deliverance!</p>
               <p>A like Addreſs was made by the ſame Advice and Hand, to the King to the ſame Effect, in anſwer to that loud awakening Call, by that ſignal Blazing Star, for the promoting of the ſame grand Deſign of exalting of Chriſt, and of the Word of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And a third, ſometime after to the preſent Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> for the like End.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Paul</hi>'s manner was, accordingly <hi>Shem Acher</hi> in his place, finding ſome Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, at his firſt coming to live near <hi>London</hi> to do work for his LORD and for Souls, they agreeing to deſire him thereunto, and expreſſing this deſire to him, that, ſeeing they were a few ſcattered Sheep without a Shepherd, not being fully then ſatisfied to join in Church Fellowſhip with any particular Church as ſo conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, and ſo walking in <hi>London,</hi> they declaring their being ſatisfied in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and in him, that, he would adminiſter the LORD's Supper unto them; which, after Conference with them, and divers of them having profited under his miniſterial Labours, and having been baptized by him, accordingly he did at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnal-Green</hi> in the year ſeventy four, withal declaring both he and they, that, this was a providential Communion in all the Ordinances of Chriſt's new Spiritual Houſe towards the latter-day-Glory, ſo far, as for the preſent according to our Scripture-Light they can regularly come at them, and ſo long as the LORD ſhould continue them ſomewhat near together in their Dwellings: this was aſſented unto and agreed upon by thoſe baptized Believers, and Seventh-day-Sabbath-Obſervers. A little after this, ſome difference in Judgment ariſing amongſt them, which <hi>Shem Acher</hi> foreſaw, and told it unto ſome, a remnant of them, who were more of one Mind, agreed at a meeting in ſeventy five, to own the LORD Jeſus Chriſt to be the one and only LORD and Lawgiver to their Souls and Conſciences, and the Holy Scriptures of Truth, as the one and only Rule of Faith, Worſhip, and Life, according to which they were to judg of all their Caſes. Then did they paſs into a Church: For, at that meeting upon this Agreement, without any particular Church-Covenant about controverted Matter, they did firmly lay all their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottoming and building upon this Rock and Foundation, even upon Chriſt and upon his Word.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57500:15"/>
               <p>A little before their thus paſſing into this Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> State and Relation, the two Sabbath Churches in the City deſired his Labours at ſometimes with them in the uſe and exerciſe of his Gifts, which he conſented to upon their importunity, the LORD aſſiſting him and proſpering of his Labours upon the Hearts of ſeveral, whoſe longings ſtill encreaſed, to enjoy more of his Miniſterial Labours, after that he had gathered ſome Diſciples of Chriſt and was in a Church-way with them, and had a diſtinct Meeting-place in the ſame City, where he met with the Church, and others who gave their Attendance at that Aſſembly, where his ſervice was accepted of the Saints; ſo that, they were mutually refreſhed, whereby they had in much experience a ſavoury taſte of the Spirits of one another, divers of the Brethren and Siſters of one of thoſe two other Churches of Sabbath-keepers imparting ſome of their inmoſt Caſes unto <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> who has here upon this occaſion a weighty Caſe to propound.</p>
               <p>As to the Matter of Fact, which is atteſted to be true by the whole Church, who knew what doth follow, with whom he doth walk; <hi>Shem Acher</hi> doth ſuppoſe, a Siſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of another Sabbath-Church in the ſame City, imparted this Caſe of her Soul unto him, reporting to him, that, for ſome years ſhe had been mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h oppreſſed in Heart, diſtreſſed in Spirit, broken and diſtempered in her bodily Conſtitution, for want of that Spiritual Life and Liberty, Purity and Peace, Sweet and Satisfaction, which ſhe enjoyed not where ſhe ſat before; but ſince ſhe came under the Miniſtry of <hi>Shem,</hi> her communicated Experience is, that ſhe has met with that Preſence of the Holy good Spirit, and of Grace ſealed upon her Heart here, to her Edification, Comfort, and Healing; whereupon ſhe deſired to be in full Communion with <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> and with the Friends in Church-Fellowſhip with him; he laying this Gaſe in the ſeveral Circumſtances of it to Heart (the particulars whereof he is not willing to inſiſt upon, as being loth to exaſperate the Spirits of any concerned) imparted it to the Friends in Goſpel-Fellowſhip, who upon due conſideration and ſerious deliberation, unanimouſly received her into Church-Communion, the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comforting Effects whereof, were quickly felt in her Spirit, Soul, and Body too through Grace.</p>
               <p>Upon this Caſe, as to the Matter of Right, ariſeth this Queſtion, Whether, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Circumſtances, either this Siſter in ſo coming off from that former Church, or the Church with <hi>Shem Acher</hi> in ſo receiving of her, have ſinned and tranſgreſſed the Laws and Rules of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>That, neither ſhe nor they are under Guilt in this Matter, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> and the Friends with him do give theſe following Scripture-Arguments and Reaſons, bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed upon Scripture-Grounds and Teſtimonies.</p>
               <p>One Argument is drawn from the Principal Efficient Cauſe of a Church, who is <hi>Jehovah Aelohim.</hi> He it is <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 100. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; 102. 18. &amp; 149 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. Iſa. 43. 1, 7, 15, 21. &amp; 44. 2, 21, 24. &amp; 51. 13. &amp; 54. 5. 1 Cor. 1. 2. Pſal. 47. 2. Acts 20. 28. Zech. 2. 8. Rev. 2. 1. Iſa. 27. 2, 3. Deut. 32. 28. Iſa. 43. 1. &amp; 63. 16. Act. 20. 21. Gal. 1. 3. Eph. 5. 25, 26, 27, 29, 30. Col. 1. 14. Heb. 13. 20. Rev. 1 5, 6, 17, 18, 19, 20. &amp; 5. 9. &amp; 14. 4. Prov. 9. 1. Mat. 16 18, 19. Heb. 3. 3, 4, 6.</note> who createth, and maketh a Church. He calleth it, purchaſeth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. He feeds it, he loves it as the Apple of his Eye; He walketh in the midſt of it; He protecteth it; He doth all things for it; He dwelleth there; He formeth and frameth it; He is the Father of it: As the Father, and his Son, and Holy Spirit, is thus to his Church; ſo alſo is Chriſt the Mediator, the Redeemer of his Church, its Saviour, Deliverer, Purchaſer, Buyer, Builder.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> ſhe has <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 5.</note> given up her ſelf, which is the Primary, Chief, and Special Relation, on which all higher Church-Communion and Fellowſhip is firmly and principally founded: it is to ſuperſede and over-rule all ſecondary, meaner, commoner, and ſubſervient Relations, on which all lower Brotherly and Siſterly Communion and Fellowſhip is more remotely, ſubordinately, and leſs principally founded. No after-inconſiderate-Obligation to any People can take away a former higher Obligation, whereby a right doth accrew to another, eſpecially this other being the Supreameſt over all.</p>
               <p>The Argument runs thus.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> in Father, Son, and Holy Spirit; if the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, God-Man, who is the principal Efficient Cauſe of his Church, who createth it, and maketh it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If he have this way evidently diſpoſed of her, where ſhe may moſt and beſt honour and enjoy him in all Church-Ordinances, and Church-Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, according to Word-Rule, ſhe having thus given up her ſelf to him, in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, chief and ſpecial Relation; then neither ſhe nor we are under Guilt ſo far in this Matter.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57500:16"/>
               <p>But <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> in Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, God-Man, who is the Principal Efficient Cauſe of his Church, who createth it, and maketh it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> has this way evidently diſpoſed of her, where ſhe may moſt and beſt honour and enjoy him in all Church-Ordinances and Church-Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions according to the Word-Rule, ſhe having thus given up her ſelf to him in a primary, chief and ſpecial Relation.</p>
               <p>And Therefore, neither ſhe nor they are under Guilt ſo far in this Matter.</p>
               <p>Another drawn from the Inſtrumental Efficient Cauſe of the Church of God, which is <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 23, 24, 26. Col. 1. 2,—7. Acts 2. 41,—47 &amp; 4. 4. &amp; 5. 14. &amp; 6. 1, 7. &amp; 8. 4, 12. &amp; 9. 31. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. 21, 24. &amp; 13 49. &amp; 14. 1. &amp; 16. 5. &amp; 17. 4, 12, 34. &amp; 18. 4, 8. &amp; 19. 19, 20. &amp; 20. 28. Mat. 24. 45. Joh. 21. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 16, 17. Act. 20 28. 1 Pet. 5. 2. 1 Tim. 3. 1. Heb. 13. 7, 17. 1 Pet. 51,—5.</note> both, ſound Doctrine, grounded firmly upon the Word, and faithfully Preached, by which the Church is born and propagated: and alſo, the Miniſter or Miniſters of Chriſt, who preach this ſound Doctrine, and do adminiſter in the Church, who do feed the Church, who overſee it, who watch over it, who rule and diſcipline it, who pray for it, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>They argue thus.</p>
               <p>If this Siſter have put her ſelf in the ſame City under ſuch ſound Doctrine, grounded firmly upon the Word faithfully preached, and under ſuch a Miniſtry, which is the inſtrumental Cauſe of a Church of Chriſt, where ſhe has wholeſome Food more proper and ſuited to her Caſes, by which ſhe is better nouriſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is every way more advantaged, more profited better cared and provided for, in all Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals, as to a Church-State-and-Relation, for Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Converſation, having all inſtituted Ordinances more fitted to her Spiritual State, Frame, Acting, and Appetite, her Soul-caſes more directly ſpoken unto, there being more of a ſweet Spiritual Accord in Principles, and other ways between her Spirit and the preſent Church with whom ſhe walketh, which ſhe could not for ſeveral years ſo enjoy in the other Society; then neither ſhe nor they are unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Guilt ſo far in this Matter?</p>
               <p>But, this Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>Another is drawn from the Material Cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eph 1. 22. &amp; 4. 15, 16. &amp; 5. 23. Col. 1. 18. &amp; 2. 19. Heb. 2. 15, 16, 17, 18 &amp; 4. 4. 15, 16. Rom. 8, 9, 11, 14. Eph. 4. 3, 4, 5, 6. Song of Songs throughout. Iſa. 33. 22. Eph. 5. 23. Joh. 10. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Heb. 3 6. &amp; 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2 or. 11. 2. Eph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4 4, 15, 16. &amp; ver. 11, 12, 13. Mat. 11. 20. &amp; 28. 18, 19, 20.</note> The LORD Jeſus Chriſt is the ſupream Head of his Church, the material Cauſe of the Church, of the ſame Nature, partaker of the ſame Fleſh and Blood with all the living Members of his Church, made like him in all, except Sin: the ſame ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, who is in Chriſt, refideth in the Church, and in all and every of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated Members thereof, who by this Spirit are united to Chriſt, animated en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouled by this Spirit: from this Chriſt doth flow all Spiritual Life and Motion to his Church: he is by far more excellent than the Church; he has the Empire and Government over the Church; he gives Laws to the Church; he is the Saviour of it; he doth acknowledg it, and is acknowledged by it, he is indiſſolubly united to it by the ſtrongeſt, cloſeſt Bond; no other beſides him is Head of the Church; he is the Husband of it, he fitly joyns the Members of it together into one Body; he doth gift the Church, and its Officers; he is always preſent with it, having all Authority and Power in Heaven and on Earth given to him for theſe holy good Purpoſes.</p>
               <p>It is here thus argued.</p>
               <p>If Chriſt in all this have ſo framed, inclined and led this Siſter, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſhe have in all this thus ſubmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted unto Chriſt in the fitteſt and beſt way, where ſhe according to her raiſed expectation has received more of the Holy Spirit, and of influences from Chriſt, as a living Member under this Church, as the only Head, and as the Supream Material Cauſe of the Church; then neither ſhe nor they are under Guilt ſo far in this Matter.</p>
               <p>But, Chriſt in all this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>This was drawn from the Material Cauſe of the Church Supream.</p>
               <p>A further Argument ſhall be drawn <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 15, &amp; 12. 27. Eph. 1. 22, 23. &amp; 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4, 12. &amp; 5. 23. 30. Col. 1. 18, 24. &amp; 2. 19. Joh. 10. 16. 1 Cor. 1. 2. <hi>and the Titles of</hi> Paul'<hi>s other Epiſtles to the Churches.</hi> Heb. 12. 23. Eph. 4. 16.</note> from the inferior Material Cauſe of a Church of Chriſt, which are the Elect, Believers, and Saints, who are the Members and the Body of Chriſt, and have mutual care of and for one another, Communion with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57500:16"/> one another, and are jointly helpful to each other, and do faithfully and friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y diſcharge the Goſpel Duties of Church-Fellowſhip mutually towards one anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch as mutual conſidering of one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is here, thus argued.</p>
               <p>If this Siſter have joined her ſelf there in Church-Fellowſhip with them amongſt thoſe, whom ſhe charitably hopes may be ſuch living Fellow-Member<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Chriſt with her, more and better ſuited to her Spirit in ſuch a Church-way of Spiritual Incorporation, where ſhe has more freedom and better agreement in her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>an, more Spiritual Communion, more really expreſſed and acted helpfulneſs. as to Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals, more enjoyment of the Goſpel-Duties of Church-Fellowſhip mutually to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one another, than in that Society where ſhe was before, and all this as the Inferior Material Cauſe of the Church; then neither ſhe non they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>Another is drawn from the Formal Cauſe of a Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Formal Cauſe, or Form, or <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 4. 3, 4. Acts 2. 41, 47. &amp; 4. 32. &amp; 9. 31. 1 Cor. 12. 12, 13, 27. &amp; 10 17. &amp; 1. 10, 11. Phil. 2. 1,—5. Eph. 1. 21, 22, 23. &amp; 3. 17. &amp; 2. 19. Rom. 8. 9. 1 Joh. 4. 13. Col. 1. 18. &amp; 2. 19. Eph. 5. 32.</note> that which doth give a ſpirited Life, Being and Motion, is the uniting Spirit of the LORD enlivening the Church-Body, and that Union of Believers in the Spirit with Chriſt as the Head, and with and another as Fellow-Members of the ſame Myſtical Body.</p>
               <p>The Argument thus preſenteth it ſelf to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>If the Spirit of this Siſter in Experience according to the Word, both were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Admiſſion, and hath been and ſtill is ſince her Admiſſion amongſt ſuch more knit and united by the Holy Spirit, in Holy Spiritual Union to Chriſt and to theſe Fellow-Members, where ſhe has more of ſpirited Life, Being, and Motion, than when amongſt thoſe with whom ſhe walked in Society withal before, which was broken off and taken away from her as to the quickneſs and comfort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, as to the former Church, in whoſe fellowſhip ſhe could not any longer to any good ſatisfaction continue, and where ſhe had little or no expectation after much proof and long waiting, to have it otherwiſe as the Caſe was circumſtanced, ſhe being now made more ſenſible, that her Spirit doth more cloſe with, and is more one in Union and Communion with the Spirit of that Church in this Church-way of Ordinances, with whom ſhe is joined, and all this as the Formal Cauſe, or Form, or that which doth give a Spirited Life, Being and Motion to a Church; then neither ſhe, nor they, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, the Spirit of this Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore.</p>
               <p>From the Final Cauſe a ſtrong Argument may be drawn, and its right words are forcible.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Iſa. 43. 7, 21. Jer. 13 11. &amp; 14. 21, Eph. 5. 26, 27. &amp; 4. 11, 12, 13, 15, 16. 1 Cor. 12. 13. &amp; 10. 16, 17. Luke 12. 32. 1 Cor. 14. 3, 26, 40. &amp; 10. 16, 17. 2 Cor. 13. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> The Final Cauſe, or the great End or Ends, for which <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> has formed his Church, and for which Chriſt gave and delivered up himſelf, in reſpect of him is his Glory, the Honour of his Name in the World, that it may be as a Throne of his Glory; the purging and cleanſing of his Church and People; their enjoyment of Spiritual Priviledges and Benefits purchaſed by the Blood of Chriſt, their nouriſhing, growing more up into, and further perfecting in Chriſt; their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving more of all Spiritual Supplies from Chriſt, their mutual Edification, being built up more and more in their moſt holy Faith, their poſſeſſing of ſigned, ſealed, witneſſed, delivered free gracious Grants from the Father through his Son, by his Spirit in the word of his Truth of Grace, and at the laſt their everlaſting Happineſs, in a clear ſight and full enjoyment of the Heavenly Glory in his Eternal Kingdom, in the better Country: In the mean time, the giving and receiving of Spiritual Alms, Bread and Wine, to hungry thirſting Souls, as neceſſary Proviſion in their Voyage, whilſt here in the way.</p>
               <p>The Argument is thus formed.</p>
               <p>If this Siſter, after long Experience, and much waiting, and earneſt Praying, could not attain the forementioned Ends of Church-Fellowſhip in that way wherein ſhe walked before; whereas ſince ſhe paſſed into Church Communion with others, the LORD has graciouſly given her to enjoy in growing Meaſures much of theſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57500:17"/> deſired Ends, and ſome good Beginnings, as ſhe hopes, of the filling up of theſe in the Heavenly Country, where ſhe longeth and waiteth, prayeth and prepareth to be with her LORD in the moſt pure and Glorious Church; then neither ſhe nor they, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, this Siſter, after long Experience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>Two other Arguments may be drawn from the juſt Right and due Property of this Siſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 21, 22, 23. Deut. 18. 6, 7, 8.</note> The Gifts and Graces and Experiences of all the Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt in the ſame City eſpecially, being one with Chriſt and his Word, in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel, are a part of every Believers Portion there, which they may uſe as their own, eſpecially when actually, really more to their Edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cation, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence doth give opportunity.</p>
               <p>From hence it is thus argued.</p>
               <p>If this Siſter in this have acted, but as her juſt Right and due Property is, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy this part of her Spiritual Portion, and if they have but done her Right in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her what is her own, as due unto her, then neither ſhe nor they, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Siſter in this has acted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>Alſo from her lawful Liberty.</p>
               <p>This Siſter reſerved a Liberty, if ſhe found in Experience, that her continuing there were not to her Satisfaction and Edification, that, then it ſhould be free to joyn her ſelf to ſome other Church of the ſame Faith and Order, in the main, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Believers, and Seventh-day-Sabbath-Obſervers, where ſhe might be more to her Soul-profiting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 13. 7, 8. Prov. 3. 27, 28. Pſal. 11. 7. Iſa. 51. 22, 23. 1 Pet. 5. 3. 1 Cor. 7. 23. 2 Cor. 1. 24. Ezek. 13. 22.</note> they are to render unto all their Dues, to owe no Man any thing: they may not withhold good from them to whom it is due, (from the owners thereof) when it is in the power of their hand to do it, they may not ſay to their Neighbour, Go, and come again, and to Morrow they will give, when they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it by them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> none may lord it over her, or exerciſe Dominion over her Faith, but ſhould be helpers of her Joy: the righteous and juſt <hi>Jehovah</hi> loveth Righteouſneſs, or Juſtice; he would not have any to make the Hearts of ſuch righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Ones ſad, whom he hath not made ſad.</p>
               <p>The Argument is thus framed.</p>
               <p>If this Siſter in thus coming off from the former Church, joyning of her ſelf to others, have but claimed and taken what was her lawful juſt Liberty, and upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted by others, have found in Experience, that, ſhe has not gone back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but preſſed forward towards the approaching Glory of the latter-day; then, neither ſhe nor they, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Siſter in thus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore.</p>
               <p>Further Arguments may be drawn from common and ſpecial Bonds both of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>In general, and in common they being with her Fellow-Chriſtian Diſciples, and not only ſo, but alſo in particular and in ſpecial, as they are Fellow-Baptized Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Sabbath Keepers, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 13, 27. Joh. 10 9, 19, 11, 16, 28. &amp; 21. 15, 16, 17. Ezek. 34. throughout. Eph. 4. 11, 12, 13.</note> they, ſtanding related to this Siſter in the Duties and Priviledges of Church-Fellowſhip and Communion, and having by the Evangelical Miniſtry amongſt them done in this but ſuch a compaſſionate charitable Office, as to take a ſickly Sheep into ſuch a Paſture, where Chriſt has given her both Food and Reſt, who, as her Caſe was circumſtanced, was Conſumptive before, and in danger to be made a Prey of.</p>
               <p>Hence they thus argue.</p>
               <p>If they ſtood related in the Duties and Priviledges of Church-Fellowſhip and Communion to this Siſter, not only by general common Bonds, as being with her Fellow Chriſtian Diſciples, but alſo in particular and ſpecial, as they are Fellow-Baptized Believers and Sabbath Keepers, and have by the Evangelical Miniſtry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them done in this but ſuch a compaſſionate charitable Office, as to take a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57500:17"/> weak ſickly Sheep into ſuch Paſture, where Chriſt has given her both Food and Reſt; who as her Caſe was circumſtanced, was Conſumptive before, and in danger to be made a Prey of, knowing no other Remedy, as a means, for her Spiritual Relief under her diſtreſſing Caſe; Then neither ſhe nor they, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, we ſtood related, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>Further, under this Head of Argument.</p>
               <p>It is warrantable by the Laws of concreated both Nature and Grace, to take in by Coadunation that, which doth run to them by <note n="*" place="margin">Phil 2. 19, 20, 21. Acts 9. 26, 27, 28. Judg. 20. 11. 1 Sam. 18. 1. 1 Chron. 12. 17. Col. 2. 2, 19. Rom. 12. 16. 2 Chron. 11. 13, 14, 15, 16. Act. 19. 8, 9. Song of Songs throughout. Eph. 4 4, 5, 6.</note> Spiritual Connaturality. Every thing haſteneth to join with its Connatural: and what is Connatural doth readily receive it, and this by the Laws and Rules both of the firſt and new Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by ſympathetical Coadunation; like will to like. Thus in Minerals, if divers Metals be melted together, they joyn each to that of its own kind; and Beaſts and Birds will flock together amongſt thoſe of their own kind; if you put Chymical Spirits and Oyl into one and the ſame Glaſs, tho by violence they may be jumbled and ſhaken into a commixture, yet let the Glaſs be ſet down ſteady awhile, and the Spirits will run to the Spirits, and the Oyl to the Oyl, and they will be diſtinct, and quickly tell the obſerving Eye, with whom each of them will be in Society. It is one Property of the Church of Chriſt, that it is Coadunated into an Oneneſs and Sameneſs in Goſpel-Duties and Church-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riviledges.</p>
               <p>From whence it is thus argued:</p>
               <p>If this Siſter, and They in This, have acted by the Laws and Rules of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created both Nature and Grace, She coming in, and They taking in by Coadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, there being a mutual Motion of Conſent for Church-Union and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion between Her and Them by Spiritual Connaturality in the great and main things of Experimented Chriſtianity; Then neither She nor They, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But, this Siſter, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Take one Argument more drawn from Scripture-Precepts and Precedents: <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14. 1. &amp; 15. 5, 6, 7. Joh. 22, 34, 35. &amp; 10. 16. Mat. 5, 6, 7, 13, 23, 25. chapters.</note> Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and other ordained Miniſters, did, according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Rules, ſo receive Diſciples, Believers, and Saints into Church-fellowſhip. Where <hi>Paul</hi> made or found thorow-Diſciples of Chriſt, walking in all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of the LORD blameleſs, in any City, or Town, or elſewhere, there he held actual Providential Communion with them, as is proved in the Margent, pag. 21, concerning <hi>Paul.</hi> In one and the ſame City, where were many preaching Miniſters, and ſeveral Congregations, the believing baptized Diſciples being ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerary, too many for only one place of aſſembling for inſtituted Worſhip, all of them at one and the ſame time; <note n="†" place="margin">Acts 2. 41,—47 &amp; 4. 4, 32. &amp; 5. 11, 14. &amp; 6. 1,—7. &amp; 7. 38. &amp; 8. 1, 3. &amp; 11. 22, 26. &amp; 12. 1, 5. &amp; 14. 26, 27. &amp; 15. 2, 3. 4, 22, 23, 25, 27. <hi>Compare alſo</hi> Acts 2. 42, 43, 44. &amp; 4. 23. &amp; 5. 42. &amp; 6. 1, 2, 5, 7, 9. &amp; 8. 1, 4, 5, 6, 12, 14. &amp; 9. 2, 20, 22, 31. &amp; 11. 19,—27. &amp; 12. 25. Acts 5. 42. &amp; 20. 20. 1 Sam. 1. 9. &amp; 3. 3. 2. Sam. 22. 7. Pſal. 18 6 &amp; 68. 29. &amp; 5. 7. &amp; 28. 2. Acts 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 2, 5. &amp; 14. 26, 27, 28. &amp; 15. 21, 34, 35, 41. 1 Cor. 1. 2. &amp; Rom. 16. 1. <hi>compared.</hi>
                  </note> yet ſo many of them as were ſuch, were as one Church, even where were ſeveral Congregated Churches, and were not ſo bound up only to hear in one of theſe Congregations, not only thoſe Miniſters who preached more commonly in ſome one of theſe Congregations; but, it was their liberty and priviledge to hear in other Congregations of the ſame City, and other Miniſters of Chriſt, teaching in the ſame City, where it was evidently more for their Edification. All the believing baptized Diſciples of Chriſt in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> are called <hi>Peter</hi>'s and <hi>John</hi>'s, and the reſt of the Apoſtles own Company, their proper ones, tho there were other of the ſeventy Diſciples, Teachers there alſo. Beſides the Temple there were ſeveral Synagogues in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which were neceſſary for Meeting-places, the number of Chriſtian Diſciples being ſo multiplied. The Apoſtles taught in other Houſes as well as in the Temple, in the Synagogues in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there being a neceſſity of many Meeting-places, when there were ſo many myriads, ſo many ten thouſands of Believers, as the <hi>Greek</hi> doth expreſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> tho the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation doth not ſo render it, <hi>Act.</hi> 21. 17, 20. And the more General Appellation of the <hi>Temple</hi> doth ſometimes in ſome places include the <hi>Synagogues;</hi> ſo was the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> called. There were <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues</hi> in <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> There were <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Galilee,</hi> and <hi>Samaria.</hi> There were ſeveral Preachers, Prophets, Teachers in <hi>Antioch</hi> a City of <hi>Syria,</hi> too many to be confined only to one Congregation, whom thoſe of the Church in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57500:18"/> that City might hear as they moſt could profit; eſpecially was it thus in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> There were Synagogues at <hi>Salamis,</hi> a City in <hi>Cyprus.</hi> In every City of <hi>Judea</hi> they had their Synagogues, where was Reading and Preaching every Sabbath Day. There were Churches in <hi>Syria</hi> and in <hi>Cilicia.</hi> At <hi>Corinth</hi> there was a Church, and another at <hi>Cencrea,</hi> which belonged to <hi>Corinth.</hi> And this Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> the Believers and Saints in Church-fellowſhip there are highly commended by <hi>Paul,</hi> for firſt giving up of themſelves to the LORD (Chriſt) to be wholly his, in all things to be ruled by his Will and Law, and then, under Him, unto his faithful Miniſters, ſo far as theſe did guide them by the Scripture-Rule according to Chriſt's Will therein: not only thoſe Miniſters of Chriſt who were more particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to ſome Church there, not only to <hi>Apollos,</hi> or ſome one or two more, but alſo to <hi>Paul, Cephas, Barnabas, Timothy, Titus, Sylvanus,</hi> or any other ſuch providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially teaching there, they all doing the ſame work, and being Workers together therein: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. &amp; 3. 4,—9, 22. &amp; 16. 10, 11, 12. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1. &amp; 5. 18, 19, 20. &amp; 8. 16,—24. &amp; 12. 12, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5. There were more Miniſters than one at <hi>Corinth,</hi> is clear from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 23-32.</p>
               <p>This with more of the like Collections from Scripture, might be improved to great and good uſes, when the Churches ſhall be in a ſpirit and frame for it.</p>
               <p>At preſent they thus argue from hence: If <hi>Shem Acher</hi> and thoſe with him, have received into Church-fellowſhip this Siſter according to the forementioned Precepts and Precedents by Scripture-Warrants and Rules: Then neither She nor They, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> and thoſe with him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>Thus have they made it appear by many ſolid Arguments, that they have not done, without great Cauſes and weighty Reaſons, what they have done in the Caſe of this Siſter. If any will be returning an Anſwer, it is deſired and expected, that he would, according to what he ſees here before him, firſt, ſet down the Scriptures, and then argue from thoſe Scriptures.</p>
               <p>They have brought in their Teſtimony for their LORD in this matter, He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given Authority to his Officers, for the Edification of his Churches and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and not for their Deſtruction. They can do nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth. They love the Truth and Peace; they purſue Holineſs, and would have their All to be done in Love, in that Love which is of God, and is brotherly and unfeigned. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 8, 10. &amp; 13. 8, 11. <hi>Rom. 15. 4,—7. Zech. 8. 19. Heb. 12. 14. 1 Cor.</hi> 16. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 13, 15. Act. 26. 9, 10, 11. 1 Tim. 14, 15, 16, 17. Act. 9. &amp; chap. 22. &amp; chap. 26. Eph. 3. 7, 8, 9, 10, 17, 18, 19. 1 Cor. 15. 8, 9, 10. <hi>Conſider well the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Acts of the Apoſtles, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Epiſtles of</hi> Paul. Eph. 3. 8. 2 Cor. 11. &amp; 12. chap. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. 2 Cor. 4. 1, 2. &amp; 1. 12. Heb. 13. 18. 1. Cor. 15. 10. &amp; 2. Cor. 12. 11, 12. Phile. v. 9. Phil. 3. 7,—21. 2 Tim. 4 6, 7, 8.</note> He had ſound good Evidences and Aſſurances of his happy State in ſaving ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Grace. Altho in the days of his Unregeneracy he had been one of the Prime of Sinners, yet he lived to be one of the moſt eminent Exalters of free Grace, and moſt ſerviceable Inſtruments in Chriſt's hand, of any meer Man that ever lived; yet he in great Humility acknowledged himſelf leſs than the leaſt of all Saints. O what a Name of Honour has he in Scripture-Records for his Doings and Sufferings for Chriſt? How much did he commend himſelf to every Man's Conſcience in the ſight of God? having this to be his rejoycing, the Teſtimony of his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that, in Simplicity and Sincerity according to God, not in fleſhly Wiſdom, but in the Grace of God, he had had his Converſation in the World; being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that he had a good Conſcience, behaving himſelf well in all things. Well nigh about one third part of the New Teſtament is an Hiſtorical Narration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, who tho he were ſo ſingularly eminent, and ſo growingly excelling in edifying Gifts, and in ſanctifying Graces, and in extraordinary uſefulneſs, even to old Age, to the very laſt, yet ſtill forgetting thoſe things that were behind, he reached forth unto thoſe things that were before, preſſing toward the Mark, for the Price of the high Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus, having his Citizenſhip in Heaven; calling upon others to be Followers together of him, and to mark them who walk ſo, as they had him for an enſample, ſo far as he followed Chriſt, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57500:18"/> when he had fought a good Fight, finiſhed his Courſe, and kept the Faith, paſſed triumphingly into Glory, being well aſſured, that, there was laid up for him a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the LORD the righteous Judg would give him at that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SHEM ACHER.</head>
               <p>If towards the cloſe of this Narrative any ſerious Enquirer, do deſire to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied concerning his Spiritual State; that no trouble may remain upon their Heart and Mind to hinder their profiting under his Miniſtry, the God of all Mercy, of all Grace, and of all Conſolation has treaſured up much in the Heart of <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> as matter of ſelf-emptying and of Soul-humbling, yet withal of exalting of <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> in Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, of advancing of Chriſt that All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonderful one, God-Man: How unſearchably rich has this Grace, how admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly free has this Love been!</p>
               <p>A Spiritual Diſcerner may gather much together by way of Evidence, out of the foregoing Hiſtory of <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s Life; one more eminent Paſſage whereof he would here revive in the Memory, becauſe it has been one of the moſt eminent excelling Experiences of his whole Life, when his more thorow Converſion, by way of Spiritual Eſpouſals, had ſuch clear full ſatisfactory ſelf-Evidence in it, as ſhines in his inner Man to this very hour, altho he had ſomewhat of it before. It is that ſhining Manifeſtation of thoſe glorious Appearances of Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, in the Heavenly Glory to <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s Spirit, and of the LORD Jeſus Chriſt as to his glorified Humanity, and the ſeed of it in the North above this blew viſible Expanſe, the opening of which Myſtery may hold forth a Scripture-Light for the guiding of others, in their turning to the LORD, covenanting with him, and being eſpouſingly united to him; for, it is, where ſeriouſly, throughly, and diſcerningly performed, one of the moſt ſolemn Actions in this World. As to a Covenanting with the LORD.</p>
               <p>On the part of <hi>Jehovah.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 29. 10,—14. &amp; 30 1, 2, 3. &amp; 26. 16,—19. Pſ. 110. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He ſets his Faces before the convinced Sinner, who is now about to turn unto him.</p>
               <p>He ſhews his readineſs to paſs into a Covenant-State and Relation with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Sinner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jehovah</hi> makes gracious Offers and precious Promiſes to ſuch a returning Soul upon certain equal Terms, if it voluntarily (by his enabling and making willing thereunto) chooſe, and approvingly agree to, and readily cloſe with thoſe Terms.</p>
               <p>He declares to ſuch a Soul, that, it will be accurſed, if it either refuſe this Offer, or be falſhearted in its profeſſion of Aſſent and Conſent to theſe Terms.</p>
               <p>He raiſeth up and eſtabliſheth the Soul in ſome great expectation of receiving ſome ſpecial Good from <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſhews himſelf forward to take ſuch a Soul to himſelf, and to acknowledg ſuch a one for one of his own peculiar People.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jehovah</hi> engageth to be a God to ſuch a Soul, if the returning Sinner give (in the ſupplies of the Holy Spirit) unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to all this ſo equal a Propoſal, ſo every way for the covenanting Convert's Good.</p>
               <p>He refers this re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urning Sinner, as to what <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath ſpoken, to his own Conſcience for all this</p>
               <p>He confirms all theſe Offers and Promiſes to ſuch a Soul by Oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſits upon the Throne of his Grace, expecting an anſwer from this retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sinner unto all this.</p>
               <p>On the returning Sinners part.</p>
               <p>This Soul ſets it ſelf before the Faces of <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon ſerious deliberation, this returning Sinner is, by a day of Chriſt's Power upon it, made willingneſs, voluntarily to chooſe, and readily to like all the Terms of this Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57500:19"/>
               <p>This Soul paſſeth over actually into Covenant with <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and acknowledgeth him for its God.</p>
               <p>This covenanting Soul ſubmits to the juſtneſs of the threatning Curſe, if the Soul be falſe-hearted, unfaithful in this Covenant.</p>
               <p>The Soul is made ſenſible of <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s great Kindneſs, in making ſo free and gracious an Offer to it.</p>
               <p>The covenanting Convert, doth preſent, give, and reſign up his whole Self, Body, Soul, and Spirit, to this <hi>Jehovah</hi> to be wholly one of his, altogether and only at his Command, Will and Diſpoſal.</p>
               <p>The Soul believingly particularly applyeth this <hi>Jehovah</hi> to it ſelf, as its own God in Covenant.</p>
               <p>This Soul takes this <hi>Jehovah</hi> at his own Saying, being well perſuaded, that, his Word ſo confirmed by his Promiſe and Oath, which are two immutable things, is true concerning all this, and upon this Word bottometh its Faith, and adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it Self, its Salvation, its All.</p>
               <p>This covenanting Convert expecteth, that, <hi>Jehovah</hi> will make good all this, and ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l and acompliſh it in a Scripture-way, as his Word is.</p>
               <p>The Soul is duly humbled under all this, going out of it ſelf, off from all meer Creatures, and away from all dependance on any Duty it doth perform, to receive all its Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Redemption from the Father freely, through Chriſt purchaſingly, by the Holy Spirit in workingly, giving all the Glory to <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> reſolving in his Strength, to know, keep and do, all the Words of this Covenant.</p>
               <p>Somewhat of the manner of Spiritual Eſpouſing at that remarkable time of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Viſion and Revelation, was thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Acher,</hi> having a diſtinct view, by an Eye of Faith, in a more than ordinary way and manner, of the Father as the Father, of the Son as the Son, of the Holy Spirit as the Holy Spirit; did orderly paſs, being helped from on High thereunto, and aſſiſted therein, into a diſtinct mutualneſs of ſuch ſolemn Contract between him and every one of theſe, which took up ſome time in his particular application ſeverally to each from that Scripture, Iſa. 54. 5. <hi>Thy Husbands thy Maker: Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah Aelohim</hi> ſo commending Himſelf, his Beauty, his Goodneſs, his every-way Amiableneſs and Lovelineſs, to <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s choiſe, ſo utterly altogehter unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſuch an unexpreſſible Favour in ſuch a way of condeſcending Grace, drawing <hi>Shem</hi>'s Heart with ſuch Bands of a Man, and ſuch Cords of Love, in working and outcalling ſuch anſwerable Affections from him, towards each of them, and ſo knitting and uniting his very Heart and Soul to every one, as his Tongue cannot utter the whole of; he had rather leave the reſt to the admiring Meditations of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Believers, who have in any good growing meaſures felt and enjoyed the ſame, than to expoſe any more of this at preſent to publick view. Only ſo it was, that <hi>Jehovah</hi> himſelf approved of what then paſſed between him and <hi>Shem,</hi> the ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witneſs whereof was never wholly withdrawn ſince that time to this day, but ſtill abides and lives there; tho he have been exerciſed with many humbling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, buffeting Temptations, boiſtrous Corruptions, blaſphemous Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diſtreſſing Caſes ſince that ſignal Honour: The LORD hath ſince that Contract all along provided for <hi>Shem</hi> as for one wedded to him, and the eſpouſing knot between them is declared indiſſoluble.</p>
               <p>He doth not by this ſay, that the LORD was never graciouſly at work upon his Heart before; for he has brought in ſome other Teſtimonies for that, in ſome choice Experiences before this more eminent Favour and Honour, tho for ſeveral years in his younger time, the work were more from a Spirit of Bondage to Fear, as has alſo been expreſſed; one time more eſpecially, when upon Faſting and Prayer, as he remembers, being under the Terrors of the LORD, he was ſummoned to appear before the Bar of God's Juſtice, to anſwer unto ſuch Charges as were to be brought in againſt him, which were ſo many, ſo heinous, and criminal, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, before the actual paſſing of the Sentence, condemned in the Court of the tranſgreſſed Law, in the Court of Divine Juſtice, and in the Court of his own guilty Conſcience, he was cloſe and home put unto it; Whether, he would ſubmit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57500:19"/> to the Sentence of the Judg were it for everlaſting Condemnation by an Act of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or for Eternal Salvation by an Act of Grace and Mercy, and whether he would acknowledg God to be juſt and righteous therein, if he ſhould condemn him by an irreverſible Sentence to be deſervedly miſerable.</p>
               <p>Thoſe, whoever were thus exerciſed, cannot but apprehend, what Horrours and Fears did now ſurprize and overwhelm <hi>Shem Acher:</hi> yet was it not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Holy Spirit framed him to ſuch a ſubmiſſion and acknowledgment, which with Tears and broken Language he expreſſed and declared, and ſo threw himſelf all along with his Mouth in the Duſt, as at the Feet of his Judg, not knowing at firſt, whether he ſhould be ſtruck dead, and damned upon the place or not: But, the LORD quickly after pronouncing how juſtly <hi>Shem</hi> had deſerved to be curſed for ever, yet that Chriſt was made a Curſe for him, and preſently an Act of Grace in the free and full forgiveneſs of his many and great Sins was drawn up, ſigned, ſealed, and delivered, received, applyed, and witneſſed to his Soul: the Crown of all be on the Head of the free Forgiver! ſince which ſignal Pardon, <hi>Shem</hi> has not, that he remembers, had almoſt any conſiderable fears of Hell at all, to ſpeak of, at any time upon him.</p>
               <p>Thus there is <note n="*" place="margin">Mat, 18. 1, 2, 3, 4. Luke 22. 31, 32.</note> Converſion after Converſion. In all which Relation concerning his Converſion, Covenanting, Eſpouſing to, and with <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> he doth not impoſe his Experiences as a Rule for others to meaſure the Truth and Soundneſs of their turning to the LORD by, in all and every of the parts, degrees, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of them; provided that their Converſion be indeed true and ſerious, ſound and ſincere according to Word-warrant and approbation: it highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them to ſee well to this, and duly to examine themſelves by Scripture-Rules about it, that they do not deceive themſelves.</p>
               <p>If further Evidence be called for, he can add theſe comprehenſive Particulars.</p>
               <p>That, <note n="†" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9 3. Gen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. 5. Rom. 1 30. Mat. 15. 18, 19, 20. Mark 7. 21, 22, 23.</note> there is no one Sin in the Seed of it, in corrupt Nature, or in the Thought of it, at leaſt in the Imagination, which ever any of the Sons or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Adam,</hi> on Earth, or in Hell, for the kind of it, either thought, ſpake, or did, recorded in the Word or communicated to him by the voluntary Confeſſion of others, which he has not had both ſome ſight of, ſome ſenſe of, and ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of: yea, ſome ways worſe than ever he yet read or heard of, by inventing of ſuch evil things in the Phancy, as he doth not know any other Man or Woman in the World did ever contrive. This Univerſal, both Original and Natural Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which has ſo defiled his whole Man in all and every of the parts of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo direct a Contrariety and Enmity to and againſt that Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is in God, and in his Law, having been <hi>Shem</hi>'s Burden both Night and Day for many a long Year. <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 7. 17,—25. &amp; 8. 2, 3. &amp; 13. 14. &amp; 4. throughout. 2 Cor. 5. 19, 21. Dan. 9. 24. Rom. 3. 19, 20,—26, Iſa. 45. 24. Rev. 19. 8. Luke 7. 47. 1 Joh. 1. 9. Col. 2. 13. Iſa. 38. 17. Mic. 7. 18, 19. Pſal. 103. 12. Iſa. 43. 25. Pſal. 32. 1,-5. Rom. 1. 17. Iſa. 45. 25. Jer. 23. 6.</note> Tho he doth thank God through Chriſt Jeſus his LORD, that the Perfect and All ſufficient Sanctification of Chriſt's Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the through and perfect Obedience performed by Chriſt in the whole Courſe of his Life whilſt converſant amongſt-Men here on Earth, is imputed unto him for Juſtification in the preſence of God, and has been ſo imputed, he by Faith putting on the LORD Jeſus Chriſt, and being cloathed with his Righteouſneſs; whereby his Sins have been forgiven, caſt behind <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Back into the bottom of the Sea; paſſed by, forgotten and blotted out, and not imputed; <hi>Jehovah</hi> Chriſt being his Righteouſneſs, in which he doth ſtand righteous before the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat of God.</p>
               <p>That, he knows not any one Saint, either on Earth or in Heaven, ſo far as we have Scripture-Records of theſe in the Word, who experienced, either edifying Gift, or ſanctifying Grace, or priviledged Enjoyment, or uſeful Serviceableneſs, and ſuch like, which he doth not heartily approve of, and which more or leſs he hath not both holily with ſubmiſſion <note n="†" place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>cum Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one contendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> we am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.</note> aſpired after, and ſome ways ſo far as he is concerned in his Place and Calling had ſome workings about it, and by improving of Myſtical Memberſhip applied as his own.</p>
               <p>That, he knows nothing, either in a whole Chriſt, or in the whole Word of Chriſt, of Holineſs or of Righteouſneſs, which he would not have an univerſal growing Knowledg of, and Conformity and Obedience to, in all things in his whole Man.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57500:20"/>
               <p>That, all theſe have been carried on for ſeveral years by a very ſharp Conteſt, and continued Conflict within, more eſpecially againſt the univerſal Corruption of his Nature, which has very ſlily and ſometimes fiercely aſſaulted him; yet ſo, as that tho there have been many a Foil and Fall in ſome particular Combates, yet, that the Iſſue of the Fights have been Victories, Spoils, and Triumphings.</p>
               <p>This humble ingenuous Confeſſion <hi>Shem Acher</hi> doth freely make of thoſe ſecret Sins, which no Man alive can ſo charge upon him: which is one part of his Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whereby he doth conform to Chriſt's Mind <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 43. 10, 11. Lev 5. 5, 6. &amp; 22. 1, 2, 3, 7. Prov. 28. 13. 1 Joh. 1. 9, 10. Pſal. 32. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>—5. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im. 1. 13. 1 Joh. 3. 21. &amp; 4. 17. Heb. 4. 16.</note> in his Word where it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, where Promiſes are made to it, where Examples are recorded of it, and which will give him the more boldneſs in the Day of Judgment before the LORD the righteous Judg, and before Angels and Men. For theſe Conſiderations have brought his Spirit to this ſelf-ſhaming acknowledgment, ſo that he can die with the more Peace of God in his Conſcience, when the Hour ſhall come.</p>
               <p>That, the LORD hath graciouſly in ſome aſcending degree manifeſted to him, and revealed in him, that inward Myſtery of a <note n="†" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 23. Joh. 3. 3. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. Ezek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 26, 27. 1 Cor. 2. 10,—16. 2 Cor. 5. 17. Gal. 5. 16, 17,-25. Rom. 8. 1,-27. Eph. 2. 10 &amp; 4. 4, 5, 6, 15, 16, 22, 23, 24. 2 Pet. 1 3, 4.</note> New-Creature-Spirit in his regenerate State in Chriſt, as diſtinct by a New Creation from his own natural conſtitutive Eſſential parts as a Man, and from the Holy Spirit, who was, is the begetter of it, by the immortal Seed of the Word, and as contrary to, that Evil Spirit Satan, and to the Spirit of the World, it being of that ſame Spirit, which Chriſt as Mediatoral Head received without meaſure; and is one of the higheſt Advances of a Believer in a growing and withal an humble frame to partake of the Divine Nature.</p>
               <p>That, <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 10. Gal. 2. 20. 2 Tim. 2. 1. 1 Joh. 1. 3. 2 Cor. 13. 14.</note> the Steps and Degrees of this Spiritual Growth have been more and more out of corrupt ſelf, off from idolized Creatures, away from Duty-dependan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, into more and more of a State of Grace, through and by that into a Life of and in Chriſt, and through and by him into a Diſtinctneſs and Orderlineſs of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Father as the Father, with the Son as the Son, and with the Holy Spirit as the Holy Spirit, and thence into a more raiſed Communion with <hi>Jehovah</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>That, all through <note n="†" place="margin">Gal. 1. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> went to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to viſit <hi>Peter,</hi> ſo to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him as that, he might know from him, or declare to him the Hiſtory o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Perſons and of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> things, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of Church Affairs. Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Shem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> given the Hiſtory of his Life, of his Call to the Miniſtry, of his perfecting of Baptiſm, of his Converſion, of his Evidences of Grace, of his Church-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſomewhat of an Hiſtory of ſome others who have oppoſed him.</note> this Hiſtorical Narrative, he bleſſeth <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> that ſtill more or leſs he has been preſſing onward, and going forward, as the growing-Light of his Age has been, not declining nor going backward in Principle, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſomewhat in that void ſpace of his time at the Univerſity, but getting upward to come at the top of all, having many a contrivement and endeavour to promote the greateſt and the beſt Ends, particularly thoſe that do relate to the latter-day-Glory; which in all the kinds and degrees thereof, he knows not to have been ſo in the Heart and Mind of the moſt eminent Believer and excelling Saint alive on this Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> having been for many years, through Grace and Mercy obtained from his LORD, <hi>Shem Acher</hi>'s State, Frame, and Acting, to come up in ſome anſwering growing proportionedneſs to all the requirements of Chriſt's Mind and Will in the whole Scriptures, that he might be a Man after Chriſt's own Heart, who enabled thereunto by the Holy Spirit, might fulfil all Chriſt's Wills, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 22. and might ſo ſerve his own Generation by the Will of God, before he fall on ſleep, <hi>ver.</hi> 36. ſtanding perfect and compleat, or, filled up, in all the Will of God, <hi>Col. 4. 12. Heb.</hi> 6. 1, 2. and ſo may be able in ſome good meaſure to anſwer theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of his LORD and Judg, What doſt thou more? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 47, 48. what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling, what exceeding thing, wherein goeſt thou beyond others? What Grace, what Grace, what Grace (which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion doth tranſlate three times, what Thank) haſt thou? <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 32, 33, 34. that, according to that Promiſe, (For ſo it ſhould be rendred in the Future Tenſe, ye ſhall therefore be Perfect, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 <hi>pl. future 1 Indic. ab</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſum) Mat.</hi> 5. 48. he may be ſtill at perfecting work, <hi>as his Father who is in Heaven is perfect;</hi> tho ſtill he carry upon is Spirit and Heart a living Sence of ſomewhat wanting as to higher degrees, yet he would in every thing be and do ſomewhat that doth excel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 3.</p>
               <p>If any after all this will ſay, That they have now one Charge more againſt <hi>Shem Acher</hi> than they had before, in that he has ſo compared himſelf with <hi>Paul,</hi> thereby miniſtring to the Pride and Selfiſhneſs of his own Heart: Such ſhould know and conſider;</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57500:20"/>
               <p>That, as he muſt after a while give an account of his writing of this Narrative, and of his Aims and Ends in ſo writing, ſo alſo muſt they of their Judgings and Condemnings of Chriſt's Servant: who has for many years been exerciſed with very humbling Providences and Caſes to keep him lowly after the LORD's ſignal honourings of him.</p>
               <p>As for his running Parallel with <hi>Paul,</hi> the Title-Page in propounding of <hi>Paul</hi> for an example, doth expreſly give the Preheminence unto <hi>Paul,</hi> and no farther uſe the comparing, than as it doth run Parallel: There is no difference between the higheſt and the loweſt Saint, but what the Grace of God has made: and an <note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 21. 1 Joh. 2. 6. &amp; 4. 17.</note> higher and incomparabler Example than that of <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould every Believer, eſpecially every Miniſter, be conformed unto, even that of the LORD Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>Had there not been ſo many years Attempts and Endeavours by ſome to blaſt the Call of <hi>Shem Acher,</hi> and thereby to hinder the Succeſs of his Miniſtry, to the troubling the Minds and diſcouraging the Hearts, of ſeveral, who were hopefully coming on towards Chriſt in his ways, he had intended to have lodged this Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Declaration within him, and when he had died away into Glory, to have made report of it to Heavenly Fellow-Citizens, which then and there would have been more cleared up in divers Circumſtances of it, and in many more Particulars, than are here mentioned: Duty and Sin do ſtand ſometimes within an Hairs Breadth one by another; That may look like a Sin, which is a Duty, and like a Duty which is a Sin: If others will count and cenſure this as Vain-glory in him, it is known to many, that he has been neceſſitated unto it. The Searcher of Hearts doth know, that <hi>Shem Acher</hi> hath been made willing, that the Glory of theſe Holy Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſignal Honours ſhould be aſcribed in every part, and in the whole of it, unto <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> whoſe rich Grace and free Love has been in all this, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchably Rich, and exceedingly Abundant.</p>
               <p>This is that <note n="*" place="margin">Lev. 23. 37. 1 King. 8. 59. 2 Chron. 8. 14. Ezra. 3. 4. Eccleſ. 3. 11.</note> Word of the Day in the Day thereof, which was brought upon his Spirit to declare unto others; it being ſelf-evident unto him, that the LORD has put a Beauty upon this, in thus timing of it in its own proper ſeaſon; the whole whereof is now delivered over unto the Holy Spirit, to work this Hiſtory and the choiſe experiences therein, upon their Hearts, into whoſe Hands, before whoſe Eyes, or unto whoſe Ears, it may come, as is good in his Sight; and all is ſubmitted to <note n="†" place="margin">Deut. 1. 16, 17. Iſa. 8. 20. Joh. 7. 24.</note> Scripture-Counſel-Number-Meaſure-and-Weight, to Word-Rule-Tryal-Judgment-and-Determination; By a Lover and Admirer of Chriſt, and of his Word and Works.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Col. 4. 18. 1 Cor 16. 21. 2 Theſſ. 3. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Shem Acher.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SHem Acher,</hi> having been by a private Letter to a near and dear Friend advertiſed, that, he is at leaſt by the ſtrong jealouſy of one or more ſuſpected, if not down-right charged, (and this before the Hiſtorical Declaration is Printed and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed) to be guilty of two Evils, the one of ſtriving for Supremacy, the other of not walking according to Goſpel-Order, and both theſe in reference to that part of the Narrative, about receiving of a Member in ſome Caſes out of one Church in the ſame City into another Church of the ſame City, in the main of the ſame Goſpel-Faith and Order: <hi>Shem</hi> therefore to prevent, or elſe remedy and remove, any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſions that may fill the Hearts and Minds of any Reader, as alſo any ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-Blocks at which ſome unwary walkers may be offended, doth openly and freely declare; that as to the firſt of theſe, which is ſtriving for Supremacy, (tho the Seed of this, as of every other Evil, is in his Heart, as in the Heart of every Son and Daughter of <hi>Adam,</hi> as our Nature is corrupted: which he doth apprehend was one of the firſt Sins, both of the Apoſtate Angels, and of Fallen <hi>Adam, 1 Tim. 3. 6. Gen.</hi> 3. 5, 22. For, both the one and the other affected a Superiority, and Self-Exaltation above and beyond that, which was their Primitive con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reated Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency) he doth now upon this occaſion publiſh to all thoſe into whoſe Hands this Paper ſhall come, and by whom it ſhall be read or heard, that it has been quite
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57500:21"/> contrary to his both Principle and Practice for many years, he has preached openly againſt this often in Aſſemblies for inſtituted Worſhip, as Multitudes of Hearers can witneſs; he has Printed againſt it: his conſtant free publick Teſtimony brought in againſt it, in whomſoever he diſcovered it, whether Pope or Prelate, Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt or Non-Conformiſt, under all the changes of Governments and Conſtitutions, doth plead for him in this Matter, and for this Teſtimony it is, as one great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which has been taken and uſed by Men of the old Hatred and deep Enmity againſt the Purity of the Chriſtian Religion, and the Power of Practical Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who ſet up their own Human Authorities, Inventions, Inſtitutions, Edicts, and Impoſitions above and contrary to the Authority of Chriſt, and of his Wills and Laws of his written Word; for this I ſay it is, that <hi>Shem Acher</hi> has ſuffered ſo many years Impriſonment, and has been divers other ways perſecuted: and it is much upon the ſame account of oppoſing of that Church-dividing deſign and attempt in ſome of the Holy Separation, that he has ſo appeared in the forementioned Caſe, which he has referred unto <hi>Jehovah</hi> to talk with them about, <hi>Third Epiſt. of John ver.</hi> 8, 9, 10. Let this be well noted and duly conſidered, and rightly applyed. If any will be ſo far contentious, as to print the Caſe for Matter of Fact under other Circumſtances, than the Truth is, whereby to give an odious miſrepreſentation of the Caſe unto others, I am not minded to keep up any quarrel about that: but if there be any need of further reply unto that, my purpoſe is to leave it unto ſome Friend or Friends in Fellowſhip, who have kept punctual and faithful Records of what has paſſed. That Cauſe which <hi>Shem</hi> in this Paper is an Advocate for, is the Matter of Right upon ſuch a Suppoſition as this printed Paper doth expreſs.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſecond of theſe, which is, Not-walking according to Goſpel-Order, <hi>Shem Acher</hi> has this to ſay for his Defence, in the Main, both as to his Judging and Acting, That his ſtudying of the Scriptures has been at times a long while about this Church-Order according to Goſpel-Rule, and that many a Prayer he hath put up to <hi>Jehovah Aelohim</hi> for Light and Direction concerning it, that his Zeal for Chriſt's Fathers Houſe was that, which did much put him forward upon acting in this Caſe as he has; and that conſidering the ſmallneſs and fewneſs of the Number of thoſe who both in the Country, and ſince in the City, in both, for now towards twenty years laſt paſt, he doth not know any one particular Church, that doth bring all Church-Caſes more to Scripture-Rule, as our growing meaſures of Knowledg herein are, and which hath more exerciſed Church-Diſcipline than that Society of Baptized Sabbatarians do with whom he has walked, and doth walk. If after this Apology, <hi>Shem</hi> ſhall be yet further charged with Self-Partiality in his own Cauſe, he reſorts for this Parallel to <hi>Paul</hi>'s Example, 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 3, 4, 5, 6. With me it is a very ſmall thing</hi> the leaſt, <hi>that I ſhould be judged of you, or of an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Judgment,</hi> or a Man's day, <hi>yea, neither do I judg my ſelf; For I am conſcious of nothing to my ſelf, yet am I not thereby juſtified: but he who judgeth me is the LORD. Therefore judg not before the time, until the LORD ſhall be come, who ſhall alſo bring to Light the hidden things of Darkneſs, and will make manifeſt the Counſels of Hearts: and then ſhall every one have praiſe of God. Learn in us not to ſavour above that which hath been written</hi> (in the Word of Chriſt.) Tho <hi>Shem</hi> have much to plead his Cauſe in the Court of Men, yet the righteous <hi>Jehovah</hi> can find out much for which to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him in the Court of Heaven: Bleſſed be <hi>Jehovah Aelohim,</hi> who has found out a way, and has led <hi>Shem</hi> into it, whereby to juſtify <hi>Shem</hi> from that in all his Caſes, wherein he doth condemn himſelf.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. for <hi>Guillam,</hi> read <hi>Guillim.</hi> P. 3. f. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. P. 10. l. 13. f. <hi>James</hi> 5, r. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 14, 15, 16. P. 10. l. 21. f. <hi>John</hi> 3. 25, 26, 27. in the Margin, r. <hi>Mark</hi> 5. 25,—34. P. 10. l. 27, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>John</hi> 3. 25, 26, 27. let this be put into the Margin, with an Aſterick *, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore A Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 10. l. laſt but two, ſtrike out, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. and put in <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 23. 21, 22, 32. P. 11. l. 46. f. <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 18. in the Margin, r. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 18.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
